<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Adjectives</title>
  </header>

  <body>

    <p>Back to <a href="grammatihkka.eng.html">grammar main page</a>.  </p>


<p><strong>Adjectives</strong> tell what something or somebody is like, e.g. what he/she/it looks like: <em class="lg_mat">Mus lea 'rukses' biila.</em> (I have a red car.) <em class="lg_mat">Son lea 'lihkolaš'.</em> (He/She is happy.) </p>


<section>
<title>Different stems</title>

<p>Adjectives are inflected in various ways, everything depends on how many syllables are in the final foot of the word in question<!-- 2011-12-05 nno takt eng foot -->. A <strong>foot</strong> is a group of syllables where the first syllable has stress: <em class="lg_mat">nuorra</em> 'young' and <em class="lg_mat">dábálaš</em> 'ordinary' both contain one foot<!-- takt -->, even though the words have different numbers of syllables, while <em class="lg_mat">bealje-heapme</em> 'deaf' contains two feet<!-- takt -->. </p>


<p><strong>Even-syllabled adjectives</strong> have two syllables in the final foot<!-- takt --> in the nominative plural. These adjectives have strong grade in the nominative singular, and weak grade in the plural, e.g. <em class="lg_mat">nuorra - nuorat</em> 'young'. Not all adjectives have gradation, e.g. <em class="lg_mat">hávski - hávskit</em> 'fun'.</p> 
<p><strong>Odd-syllabled adjectives</strong> have three syllables in the last foot<!-- takt --> in the plural, e.g. <em class="lg_mat">suohtas - suohttasat</em> 'pleasant', <em class="lg_mat">bivnnut - bivnnuhat</em> 'favored'. The nominative singular is weak grade, and most of the other forms are strong grade, but not all nouns<!-- substantiver!! Should this be adjectives? --> with an odd number of syllables are subject to gradation. </p>
<p><strong>Contraction-stem adjektives</strong> have two syllables in the final foot<!-- takt --> in both the nominative singular and the plural. The adjektive is weak grade in the nominative singular and strong or extra strong grade in the plural, e.g. <em class="lg_mat">njálggis - njálgát stuoris - stuorrát</em>. 
</p>

</section>

<section>
<title>Gradation</title>

<p>Gradation usually occurs in the consonant cluster between the first and second syllable of a foot<!-- takt -->, e.g. <em class="lg_mat">nuorra - nuorat</em> 'young'. The <strong>strong grade</strong>, for example, occurs in the nominative singular in even-syllabled adjectives, and in the nominative plural in odd-syllabled adjektives. The <strong>weak grade</strong>, on the contrary, is observed in the consonant cluster found in the nominative plural of even-syllabled adjectives, and the nominative singular of odd-syllabled adjectives.</p>

<p>
Examples of gradation with the strong grade on the left, and the weak grade on the right. Please observe that '-i-' is considered a consonant (-j-) when i follows a vowel, and it is therefore part of the consonant cluster:
</p>
<ul>
<li>nuo<strong>rr</strong>a - nuo<strong>r</strong>at (young), fa<strong>ll</strong>i - fa<strong>l</strong>it (swift), o<strong>đđ</strong>asat - o<strong>đ</strong>as (new)</li>
<li>á<strong>rg</strong>i - á<strong>rgg</strong>it (shy), gá<strong>rž</strong>i - gá<strong>ržž</strong>it (narrow), lá<strong>ik</strong>i - lá<strong>ikk</strong>it (lazy)</li>
<li>hea<strong>dj</strong>u - hea<strong>j</strong>ut (poor, bad), bealjehea<strong>pm</strong>e - bealjehea<strong>m</strong>it (deaf)</li>
<li>čea<strong>hpp</strong>i - čea<strong>hp</strong>it (skilled), njoa<strong>hc</strong>i - njoa<strong>z</strong>it (slow), u<strong>hcc</strong>i - u<strong>hc</strong>it (little), hi<strong>ht</strong>ásat - hi<strong>đ</strong>is (slow)</li>
</ul>
<p></p>
<p>Even-syllabled adjectives can also end in a consonant in the nominative singular, such as in the words <em class="lg_mat">lihkolaš</em> 'happy', <em class="lg_mat">nuoramus</em> 'youngest'. In the inflection of these words an extra syllable is added, and the word receives two feet: ('nuo-ra)('mu-sa). Hence gradation will occur in the final foot of the word. Strong-grade forms will occur in the illative singular and essive. The examples are given with nominative singular, nominative plural and illative singular:</p>

<ul>
<li>nuoramu<strong>s</strong> - nuoramu<strong>s</strong>at - nuoramu<strong>ss</strong>ii (young)</li>
<li>lihkola<strong>š</strong> - lihkola<strong>čč</strong>at - lihkola<strong>žž</strong>ii (happy)</li>
</ul>

<p>You can read more about gradation <a href="stadieveksling.eng.html">here</a></p>

</section>

<section>
<title>Other consonant gradation</title>

<p>	Some adjectives end in consonants in the nominative singular. In North Sami, there are limitations as to which consonants can occur in word-final position, and this is where we can observe special types of consonant gradation attested in the nominative singular and the other cases. The consonants that can occur in word-final position are: "t", "s", "š", "l", "r" and "n". Here are some examples of gradation in odd-syllabled adjectives and contraction-stem adjectives:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>t > h</strong>, f.eks. bivnnut - bivnnuha (favored), čáppat - čáppahin (beautiful) </li>
<li><strong>t > d</strong>, f.eks. jaskat - jaskada (quiet) </li>
<li><strong>t > g</strong>, f.eks. ártet - ártega (strange)</li>
<li><strong>t > b</strong>, f.eks. buoret - buorebu (better)</li>
<li><strong>š > ž</strong>, f.eks. dološ - doloža (ancient)</li>
</ul>
<p>Note that the letter "š" is not always subject to gradation: <em class="lg_mat">imaš - ipmaša</em> 'miracle'<!-- 2011-12-05 Of course, this is a noun and not an adjective. -->.</p>
<p>Even-syllabled nouns<!-- shouldn't this be adjectives? --> that end in consonants are subject to similar gradation:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>š > čč</strong>, for example: lihkolaš - lihkolačča (happy)</li>
</ul>

<p>Even-syllabled adjectives are also subject to gradation in these consonants, read more about it <!-- 2011-12-05 fixing the link! adjektiver.eng.html#Stadieveksling to adjektiver.eng.html#Gradation --><a href="adjektiver.eng.html#Gradation">here</a>. </p>
<p>Some odd-syllabled adjectives that end in vowels in the nominative singular gain an extra consonant in the other forms:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>_ > g</strong>, e.g. guohca - guohccaga (rotten, rank), bahča - bahččaga (bitter) </li>
</ul>

<p>Contraction-stem adjectives ending in "-i" undergo the transition "i>j" between the nominative singular and the essive in the written language.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>i > j</strong>, e.g. čeavlái - čeavlájin (haughty), muoŧŧái - muoŧŧájin <!-- 2011-12-05 Unable to find a gloss for this ()--></li>
</ul>

</section>


<section>
<title>Attributive and predicative forms</title>
<p>Adjectives appear in <strong>attribute forms</strong> when they premodify a noun: <em class="lg_mat"> 'fiskes' viessu</em> 'a yellow house'. The attribute form remains the same regardless of the number or case of the modified noun, with the exception of the adjective <em class="lg_mat">buorre</em> 'red'. Attribute forms are given in dictionaries, posibly marked with #, e.g. <em class="lg_mat"> ruoksat, #rukses</em> 'red'.</p>
<p>When the adjective is not a premodifier of a noun, standing alone, for instance, in the predicate, it has a <strong>predicative form</strong>: <em class="lg_mat">Viessu lea 'fiskat'.</em> (The house is yellow.) <em class="lg_mat">Viesut leat 'fiskadat'.</em> (The houses are yellow.) <em class="lg_mat">Nieida lea 'nuorra'.</em> (The girl is young.) <em class="lg_mat">Nieiddat leat 'nuorat'.</em> (The girls are young.) <em class="lg_mat">Moai letne 'nuorat'. </em> (The two of us were young.) The predicative form, used in subject-complement constructions and other places where there is no subsequent noun to modify, appears in the nominative singular when the subject is in the singular, and in the nominative plural when the subject is in the dual or plural. In dictionaries, you can find the consonant appearing between the second and third syllble for odd-syllabled adjectives, e.g. <em class="lg_mat">ruoksat -d- </em>(red) - which is realized in <em class="lg_mat">ruoksadat</em> in the nominative plural. Read more about such changes <!-- 2011-12-05 changing link to correlate with section title in English version. --><a href="adjektiver.eng.html#Other+consonant+gradation">here</a>.
 </p>
</section>

<section>
<title>"Buorre" as an attribute</title>
<p>When <strong>buorre</strong> premodifies a noun, it is declined in the same way as the noun it modifies, both in number and case. "Buorre" should take the same form as the noun in a majority of the cases. Exception to this are the illative and locative singular forms. Here the premodifier "buorre" appears in the accusative/genitive form.</p>
<p></p>
<ul>
<li><em class="lg_mat">Mus lea 'buorre biila'.</em> (I have a car.) </li>
<li><em class="lg_mat">Mun oasttán 'buori biilla'.</em> (I'll buy a good car.) </li>
<li><em class="lg_mat">'Buori biillas' oažžu 'buori hatti'.</em> (You can get a good price for a good car.)</li>
<li><em class="lg_mat">Duđan dušše 'buori biilii'.</em> (I'll only accept a good car.)</li>
<li><em class="lg_mat">'Buriin biillain' olle guhkás.</em> (With a good car, you can go far.) <!-- 2011-12-05 Should the word order here be stressed? --></li>
<li><em class="lg_mat">Gádden dien 'buorren biilan'.</em> (I thought that car was a good car.)</li>
</ul>
<p></p>
<p> When the word 'buorre' premodifies a noun in the plural, it will appear in the plural, as well. In the illative and comitative plural, the word "buorre" can appear in the accusative/genitive plural.</p>
<p></p>
<ul>
<li><em class="lg_mat">'Buorit biillat' leat divrasat.</em> (Good cars are expensive.) </li>
<li><em class="lg_mat">'Buriid biillaid' lea álki vuovdit.</em> (It is easy to sell good cars.) </li>
<li><em class="lg_mat">'Buriin biillain' leat 'buorit goazanat'.</em> (Good cars have good brakes.)</li>
<li><em class="lg_mat">Liikon 'buriid/buriide biillaide'.</em> (I like good cars.)</li>
<li><em class="lg_mat">'Buriiguin/buriid biillaiguin' olle guhkás.</em> (You can go a long ways with a good car.)</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section>
<title>Comparison</title>
<p>Adjectives can be compared in three degrees: <em class="lg_mat">'unni - unnit - unnimus'</em> (small - smaller - smallest). </p>
<p>The <strong>positive</strong> form is the basic form of an adjective: <em class="lg_mat"> 'unni, boaris, stuoris'</em> (little, old, big).
</p>
<p>The <strong>comparative</strong> form of the adjective is the one used in the comparison of two people or things. The comparative ending for even-syllabled and contraction-stem adjectives is "-t": <em class="lg_mat">unnit (unni)</em> 'little' <em class="lg_mat">stuorit (stuoris)</em> 'big'. Odd-syllabled adjectives have several possible comparative endings: "-et/-eabbo", "-at/-abbo": <em class="lg_mat">boarráseabbo, boarrásabbo (boaris)</em> 'elder'. 
</p>
<p>The <strong>superlative</strong> form is the highest degree of comparison, and it is used when comparing more than two people or things. The superlative ending for even-syllabled and contraction adjectives is "-mus": <em class="lg_mat">unnimus (unni)</em> 'smallest' <em class="lg_mat">stuorimus (stuoris)</em> 'biggest'. Odd-syllabled adjectives have two possible endings: "-eamos" and "-amos":  <em class="lg_mat">boarráseamos, boarrásamos (boaris)</em> 'eldest'.  
</p>
<p></p>
<p>The comparative is used both as a premodifying attribute form and as a predicative form.</p>
<p>When the comparative forms are used as premodifying <strong>attributes</strong>, they do not undergo the inflection of the noun they modify: <em class="lg_mat">(unni: unnit mánná, unnimus mánát)</em> <em class="lg_mat">(stuoris: stuorit mánná, stuorimus mánát)</em>.</p>
<p>Note that in the premodifying, attribute position only the short comparative endings are possible in odd-syllabled adjectives: <em class="lg_mat">boaris: boarráset/boarrásat mánná, boarráseamos/boarrásamos mánát</em>.</p>
<p>When comparative forms are used as <strong>predicatives</strong>, they are inflected for number of the noun they describe. Hence a difference is made between the singular and plural.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Komparativ:</strong></li>
<li><em class="lg_mat">Elle lea 'unnit' go mun. Soai leaba 'unnibut' go mun</em>.</li>
<li><em class="lg_mat">Elle lea 'stuorát' go mun. Soai leaba 'stuorábut' go mun</em>.</li>
<li><em class="lg_mat">Elle lea 'boarráseabbo/boarrásabbo' go mun.</em></li>
<li><em class="lg_mat">Soai leaba 'boarráseappot/boarrásabbot' go mun</em>.</li>
</ul>
<p></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Superlativ:</strong></li>
<li><em class="lg_mat">Elle lea 'unnimus'. Soai leaba 'unnimusat'</em>.</li>
<li><em class="lg_mat">Elle lea 'stuorimus'. Soai leaba stuorimusat'</em>.</li>
<li><em class="lg_mat">Elle lea 'boarráseamos/boarrásamos'.</em></li>
<li><em class="lg_mat">Soai leaba 'boarrásepmosat/boarrásamosat'</em>.</li>
</ul> 
</section>

<section>
<title>Kasus</title>
<p>er bøyningsformer som markerer hvilken funksjon <strong>nomen</strong> har i setningen. Nomen er enten substantiv, adjektiv, tallord eller pronomen. I nordsamisk er det sju kasus. Adjektiv kan brukes som substantiv og bøyes da i alle kasus. Bøyningsmønsteret er det samme som for substantiver. Legg merke til at komparerte adjektiv bøyes etter den takten de har i komparert form.
</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>Nominativ</title>
<p>er kasus som angir grunnformen av nomen, f.eks. <em class="lg_mat">Nieida lea 'nuorra'</em>.</p> <p>Flertall har endingen '-t' og likestavelsesadjektiv får svakt stadium:  <em class="lg_mat">Nieiddat leat 'nuorat'</em>.</p> <p>Ulikestavelsesadjektiv har svakt stadium i entall og sterkt stadium i flertall, f.eks. <em class="lg_mat">Náhkki lea 'linis'. Náhkit leat 'litnásat'.</em>  </p><p> Kontrakte adjektiv har svakt stadium i entall og får sterkt eller ekstra sterkt stadium i flertall, f.eks. <em class="lg_mat">Gussa lea 'stuoris'. Gusat leat 'stuorrát'.</em></p> 

<p>Komparerte adjektiv bøyes også i flertall. Komparativ form av likestavelsesadjektiv og kontrakte adjektiv får ulikestavelsesstamme, med tre stavelser i siste takt i flertall. Endelsen '-t' i entall veksler med '-bu' i flertall. <em class="lg_mat"> nuorat - nuorabut stuorát - stuorábut dábálaččat - dábálaččabut. </em> 
</p>
<p>Likestavelsesadjektiv som ender på '-laš', '-vaš' og '-haš' bøyes som likestavelsessubstantiv hvis endelsen for komparativ er '-eabbo' eller '-abbo'. De korte endelsene '-at' og '-et' i entall veksler med '-abbo'/'-eabbo'-endelsene i flertall. Legg merke til at endelsen '-eabbo' har stadieveksling, med svak grad i flertall:  <em class="lg_mat"> dábálat - dábálabbot dábáleabbo - dábáleappot dábálabbo - dábálabbot.</em> 
</p>
<p>Komparativ form av ulikestavelsesadjektiv får likestavelsesstamme, med to stavelser i siste takt i flertall. De korte endelsene '-at' og '-et' i entall veksler med '-abbo/-eabbo'-endelsene i flertall. Legg merke til at endelsen -eabbo har stadieveksling, med svak grad i flertall.<em class="lg_mat"> boarráset - boarráseappot boarrásabbo - boarrásabbot. </em> 
</p>
<p>De superlative formene beholder sin opprinnelige takt, bortsett fra kontrakte adjektiv, som får likestavelsesstamme. I likestavelses- og kontrakte adjektiv er superlativendelsen '-mus', mens i ulikestavelsesadjektiv er superlativendelsen '-eamos/-amos'.  Legg merke til at endelsen '-eamos' har stadieveksling, med sterk grad i flertall: <em class="lg_mat"> nuoramus - nuoramusat dábálaččamus - dábálaččamusat stuorámus - stuorámusat boarráseamos - boarrásepmosat. </em> 
</p>
<p>Likestavelsesadjektiv som ender på '-laš', '-vaš' og '-haš' kan også bøyes som ulikestavelsessubstantiv hvis endelsen for superlativ er '-eamos/-amos'. Legg merke til at endelsen '-eamos' har stadieveksling, med sterk grad i flertall. <em class="lg_mat"> dábáleamos - dábálepmosat dábálamos - dábálamosat. </em>
 </p>
<table>
<tr><td colspan="4"><strong>NOMINATIV</strong> Skravert: svakt stadium</td></tr>
<tr><td class="fatbottom small"><strong>stammetype</strong></td><td class="fatbottom small"><strong>grad</strong></td><td class="fatbottom"><strong>entall</strong></td><td class="fatbottom"><strong>flertall</strong></td></tr>
<tr><td class="small">Likest.stamme</td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td><em class="lg_mat">nuorra</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuorat</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuorat</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuorabut</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Superlativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuoramus</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuoramusat</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábálaš</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábálaččat</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábálat, dábálet, dábáleabbo, dábálabbo, dábálaččat</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábáleappot, dábálabbot, dábálaččabut</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="fatbottom"> </td><td class="fatbottom small">Superlativ</td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">dábáleamos, dábálamos, dábálaččamus</em></td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">dábálepmosat, dábálamosat, dábálaččamusat</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="small">Likest.stamme</td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">linis</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">litnásat</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td><em class="lg_mat">litnásat, litnáset, litnásabbo, litnáseabbo</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">litnáseappot, litnásabbot</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="fatbottom"> </td><td class="fatbottom small">Superlativ</td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">litnáseamos, litnásamos</em></td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">litnásepmosat, litnásamosat</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="small">Kontr.stamme</td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuoris</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">stuorrát</em></td></tr>
<tr><td>  </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuorit, stuorát</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuoribut, stuorábut</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Superlativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuorimus</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuorimusat, stuorámusat</em></td></tr>
</table> 

</section>

<section>
<title>Akkusativ</title>
<p>er kasus som brukes for objekt, f.eks.<em class="lg_mat"> Mun oasttán 'hálbbibu'.</em> Flertallsendelsen er '-id'.</p>
<p>Likestavelsesadjektiv har svakt stadium i både entall og flertall: <em class="lg_mat">nuora - nuoraid (nuorra)</em>.</p>
 <p>Ulikestavelsesadjektiv får sterkt stadium, hvis de har stadieveksling, og i entall endinga '-a': <em class="lg_mat">litnása - litnásiid (linis),  ruoksada - ruoksadiid (ruoksat)</em>.  </p>
<p>Kontrakte adjektiv får sterkt eller ekstra sterkt stadium: <em class="lg_mat">stuorrá - stuorráid (stuoris), njálgá - njálgáid (njálggis) </em>. </p>


<p>Komparativ form av likestavelsesadjektiv og kontrakte adjektiv: endelsen '-t' i entall veksler med '-bu'. <em class="lg_mat"> nuorabu - nuorabuid (nuorat), stuorábu - stuorábuid (stuorát), dábálaččabu - dábálaččabuid (dábálaččat).  Mun oasttán 'hálbbibuid'. </em> 
</p>
<p>Komparative former med '-abbo'/'-eabbo': Legg merke til at endelsen '-eabbo' har stadieveksling:  <em class="lg_mat">litnásabbo - litnásabbuid (litnásabbo), litnáseappo - litnáseappuid (litnáseabbo)</em>.</p>
<p><em class="lg_mat"> Mun vieččan 'boarráseappo'.  Mun vieččan 'boarráseappuid'.</em>
</p>
<p>De superlative formene: <em class="lg_mat">   Mun oasttán 'hálbbimusa'.  Mun oasttán 'hálbbimusaid'.</em></p>
<p>
Legg merke til at endelsen '-eamos' har stadieveksling: <em class="lg_mat"> litnásamosa - litnásamosiid (litnásamos), litnásepmosa - litnásepmosiid (litnáseamos)</em>
<em class="lg_mat"> dábálepmosa - dábálepmosiid (dábáleamos), dábálamosa - dábálamosiid (dábálamos). </em></p>


<p>I nordsamisk er adjektivenes akkusativ- og genitivformer like.</p>

<table>
<tr><td colspan="4"><strong>AKKUSATIV</strong> Skravert: svakt stadium</td></tr>
<tr><td class="fatbottom small"><strong>stammetype</strong></td><td class="fatbottom small"><strong>grad</strong></td><td class="fatbottom"><strong>entall</strong></td><td class="fatbottom"><strong>flertall</strong></td></tr>
<tr><td class="small">Likest.stamme</td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuora</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuoraid</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuorabu</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuorabuid</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Superlativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuoramusa</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuoramusaid</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábálačča</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábálaččaid</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábáleappo, dábálabbo, dábálaččabu</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábáleappuid, dábálabbuid, dábálaččabuid</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="fatbottom"> </td><td class="fatbottom small">Superlativ</td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">dábálepmosa, dábálamosa, dábálaččamusa</em></td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">dábálepmosiid, dábálamosiid, dábálaččamusaid</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="small">Likest.stamme</td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td><em class="lg_mat">litnása</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">litnásiid</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td><em class="lg_mat">litnáseappo, litnásabbo</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">litnáseappuid, litnásabbuid</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="fatbottom"> </td><td class="fatbottom small">Superlativ</td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">litnásepmosa, litnásamosa</em></td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">litnásepmosiid, litnásamosiid</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="small">Kontr.stamme</td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td><em class="lg_mat">stuorrá</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">stuorráid</em></td></tr>
<tr><td>  </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuoribu, stuorábu</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuoribuid, stuorábuid</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Superlativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuorimusa, stuorámusa</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuorimusaid, stuorámusaid</em></td></tr>
</table> 

</section>

<section>
<title>Genitiv</title>
<p>er kasus som angir eieform: <em class="lg_mat">riggá</em> (den rikes) - <em class="lg_mat">riggáid</em> (de rikes). Genitiv brukes også i pre- og postposisjonsuttrykk, f.eks. <em class="lg_mat">'Jallaid' gaskkas lei jierbmái</em>. Flertallsendelsen er '-id'. </p>
<p>Likestavelsesadjektiv har svakt stadium i både entall og flertall: <em class="lg_mat">nuora - nuoraid (nuorra)</em>.</p>
 <p>Ulikestavelsesadjektiv får sterkt stadium, hvis de har stadieveksling, og i entall endinga '-a': <em class="lg_mat">litnása - litnásiid (linis),  ruoksada - ruoksadiid (ruoksat)</em>.  </p>
<p>Kontrakte adjektiv får sterkt eller ekstra sterkt stadium: <em class="lg_mat">stuorrá - stuorráid (stuoris), njálgá - njálgáid (njálggis)</em>. </p>


<p>Komparativ form av likestavelsesadjektiv og kontrakte adjektiv: endelsen '-t' i entall veksler med '-bu'. <em class="lg_mat"> nuorabu - nuorabuid (nuorat), stuorábu - stuorábuid (stuorát), dábálaččabu - dábálaččabuid (dábálaččat).   </em> 
</p>
<p>Komparative former med '-abbo'/'-eabbo': Legg merke til at endelsen '-eabbo' har stadieveksling:  <em class="lg_mat">litnásabbo - litnásabbuid (litnásabbo), litnáseappo - litnáseappuid (litnáseabbo). </em>
.
</p>
<p><em class="lg_mat">Dat lea 'boarráseappo' musihkka.  Son lea 'boarráseappuid' gaskkas.</em>
</p>
<p>De superlative formene: <em class="lg_mat">hálbbimusa - hálbbimusaid (hálbbimus)</em></p><p>
Legg merke til at endelsen '-eamos' har stadieveksling: <em class="lg_mat"> litnásamosa - litnásamosiid (litnásamos), litnásepmosa - litnásepmosiid (litnáseamos), dábálepmosa - dábálepmosiid (dábáleamos), dábálamosa - dábálamosiid (dábálamos)</em>
</p>
<p>I nordsamisk er adjektivenes akkusativ- og genitivformer like.</p>
<table>
<tr><td colspan="4"><strong>GENITIV</strong> Skravert: svakt stadium</td></tr>
<tr><td class="fatbottom small"><strong>stammetype</strong></td><td class="fatbottom small"><strong>grad</strong></td><td class="fatbottom"><strong>entall</strong></td><td class="fatbottom"><strong>flertall</strong></td></tr>
<tr><td class="small">Likest.stamme</td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuora</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuoraid</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuorabu</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuorabuid</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Superlativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuoramusa</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuoramusaid</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábálačča</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábálaččaid</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábáleappo, dábálabbo, dábálaččabu</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábáleappuid, dábálabbuid, dábálaččabuid</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="fatbottom"> </td><td class="fatbottom small">Superlativ</td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">dábálepmosa, dábálamosa, dábálaččamusa</em></td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">dábálepmosiid, dábálamosiid, dábálaččamusaid</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="small">Likest.stamme</td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td><em class="lg_mat">litnása</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">litnásiid</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td><em class="lg_mat">litnáseappo, litnásabbo</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">litnáseappuid, litnásabbuid</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="fatbottom"> </td><td class="fatbottom small">Superlativ</td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">litnásepmosa, litnásamosa</em></td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">litnásepmosiid, litnásamosiid</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="small">Kontr.stamme</td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td><em class="lg_mat">stuorrá</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">stuorráid</em></td></tr>
<tr><td>  </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuoribu, stuorábu</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuoribuid, stuorábuid</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Superlativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuorimusa, stuorámusa</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuorimusaid, stuorámusaid</em></td></tr>
</table> 

</section>

<section>
<title>Illativ</title>
<p>er kasus som betegner bevegelse til eller inn i noe: <em class="lg_mat"> Mun adden eanet vahkkoruđa 'boarrásebbui'. Dát lea fálaldat 'riggáide'. Mun attán vuoittu 'jođánepmosiidda'</em>. </p>
<p> Likestavelsesadjektiv har sterkt stadium, endevokalen endrer seg og man får endingen '-i': <em class="lg_mat"> árgái (árgi), jallii (jalla), hedjui (headju), dábálebbui (dábáleabbo), stuorámussii (stuorámus)</em>.
</p>  
<p>Ulikestavelsesadjektiv får sterkt stadium og '-ii': <em class="lg_mat">apmasii (amas), viššalepmosii (viššaleamos)</em>. Kontrakte adjektiv får sterkt eller ekstra sterkt stadium og endingen '-i': <em class="lg_mat">njálgái (njálggat)</em>.</p>  
<p> Flertall har endinga '-ide':<em class="lg_mat"> heajuide njálgáide čeahpimusaide viššaleappuide </em> og ulikestavelsesadjektiv får '-iidda': <em class="lg_mat">apmasiidda viššalepmosiidda nuorabuidda</em>. </p>
<table>
<tr><td colspan="4"><strong>ILLATIV</strong> Skravert: svakt stadium</td></tr>
<tr><td class="fatbottom small"><strong>stammetype</strong></td><td class="fatbottom small"><strong>grad</strong></td><td class="fatbottom"><strong>entall</strong></td><td class="fatbottom"><strong>flertall</strong></td></tr>
<tr><td class="small">Likest.stamme</td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td>nurrii</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuoraide</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuorabui</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuorabuidda</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Superlativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuoramussii</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuoramusaide</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábálažžii</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábálaččaide</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábálebbui, dábálabbui, dábálaččabui</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábáleappuide, dábálabbuide, dábálaččabuidda</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="fatbottom"> </td><td class="fatbottom small">Superlativ</td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">dábálepmosii, dábálamosii, dábálaččamussii</em></td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">dábálepmosiidda, dábálamosiidda, dábálaččamusaide</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="small">Likest.stamme</td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td><em class="lg_mat">litnásii</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">litnásiidda</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td><em class="lg_mat">litnásebbui, litnásabbui</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">litnáseappuide, litnásabbuide</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="fatbottom"> </td><td class="fatbottom small">Superlativ</td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">litnásepmosii, litnásamosii</em></td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">litnásepmosiidda, litnásamosiidda</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="small">Kontr.stamme</td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td><em class="lg_mat">stuorrái</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">stuorráide</em></td></tr>
<tr><td>  </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuoribui, stuorábui</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuoribuidda, stuorábuidda</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Superlativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuorimussii, stuorámussii</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuorimusaide, stuorámusaide</em></td></tr>
</table> 

</section>

<section>
<title>Lokativ</title>
<p>er kasus som betegner på/i/hos eller fra. Lokativ kan også fortelle hvem som har noe:<em class="lg_mat">'Jallas' ii leat ollu jierbmi. Sii soitet oažžut veahki 'riggáin'. 'Boarrásepmosiin' ii leat skuvla odne. </em></p>
<p>Endingen er '-s' i entall. Likestavelsesadjektiv får svakt stadium, ulikestavelsesadjektiv får sterkt stadium: <em class="lg_mat">apmasis (amas), boarráseappos (boarráseabbo)</em>. Kontrakte adjektiv får sterkt eller ekstra sterkt stadium: <em class="lg_mat">riggás (rikkis)</em>. </p>  
<p>Flertall har endinga -in:<em class="lg_mat"> apmasiin riggáin nuoramusain</em>.
</p>
<table>
<tr><td colspan="4"><strong>LOKATIV</strong> Skravert: svakt stadium</td></tr>
<tr><td class="fatbottom small"><strong>stammetype</strong></td><td class="fatbottom small"><strong>grad</strong></td><td class="fatbottom"><strong>entall</strong></td><td class="fatbottom"><strong>flertall</strong></td></tr>
<tr><td class="small">Likest.stamme</td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuoras</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuorain</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuorabus</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuorabuin</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Superlativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuoramusas</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuoramusain</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábálaččas</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábálaččain</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábáleappos, dábálabbos, dábálaččabus</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábáleappuin, dábálabbuin, dábálaččabuin</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="fatbottom"> </td><td class="fatbottom small">Superlativ</td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">dábálepmosis, dábálamosis, dábálaččamusas</em></td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">dábálepmosiin, dábálamosiin, dábálaččamusain</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="small">Likest.stamme</td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td><em class="lg_mat">litnásis</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">litnásiin</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td><em class="lg_mat">litnáseappos, litnásabbos</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">litnáseappuin, litnásabbuin</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="fatbottom"> </td><td class="fatbottom small">Superlativ</td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">litnásepmosis, litnásamosis</em></td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">litnásepmosiin, litnásamosiin</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="small">Kontr.stamme</td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td><em class="lg_mat">stuorrás</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">stuorráin</em></td></tr>
<tr><td>  </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuoribus, stuorábus</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuoribuin, stuorábuin</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Superlativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuorimusas, stuorámusas</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuorimusain, stuorámusain</em></td></tr>
</table> 

</section>

<section>
<title>Komitativ</title>
<p>er kasus som ofte gir betydningen "med":<em class="lg_mat">Mun hupmen muhtun 'jallain'.</em> <em class="lg_mat">Mii vuolgit dohko 'riggáiguin'.</em> <em class="lg_mat">Áhčči vuolgá 'boarrásepmosiiguin', ja eadni báhcá ruoktot 'nuoramusaiguin'</em>.    
Endinga i entall er '-in'. </p>
<p>Likestavelsesadjektiv får svakt stadium: <em class="lg_mat"> nuorain dábáleappuin</em>. </p>  
<p>Ulikestavelsesadjektiv får sterkt stadium:<em class="lg_mat"> apmasiin (amas), viššalepmosiin (viššaleamos)</em>. </p>  
<p>Kontrakte adjektiv får sterkt eller ekstra sterkt stadium:<em class="lg_mat"> riggáin (rikkis)</em>. </p>  
<p>Flertall har endinga -iguin: <em class="lg_mat">apmasiiguin jallaiguin nuoramusaiguin</em>. </p>

<table>
<tr><td colspan="4"><strong>KOMITATIV</strong> Skravert: svakt stadium</td></tr>
<tr><td class="fatbottom small"><strong>stammetype</strong></td><td class="fatbottom small"><strong>grad</strong></td><td class="fatbottom"><strong>entall</strong></td><td class="fatbottom"><strong>flertall</strong></td></tr>
<tr><td class="small">Likest.stamme</td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuorain</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuoraiguin</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuorabuin</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuorabuiguin</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Superlativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuoramusain</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuoramusaiguin</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábálaččain</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábálaččaiguin</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábáleappuin, dábálabbuin, dábálaččabuin</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábáleappuiguin, dábálabbuiguin, dábálaččabuiguin</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="fatbottom"> </td><td class="fatbottom small">Superlativ</td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">dábálepmosiin, dábálamosiin, dábálaččamusain</em></td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">dábálepmosiiguin, dábálamosiiguin, dábálaččamusaiguin</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="small">Likest.stamme</td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td><em class="lg_mat">litnásiin</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">litnásiiguin</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td><em class="lg_mat">litnáseappuin, litnásabbuin</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">litnáseappuiguin, litnásabbuiguin</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="fatbottom"> </td><td class="fatbottom small">Superlativ</td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">litnásepmosiin, litnásamosiin</em></td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">litnásepmosiiguin, litnásamosiiguin</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="small">Kontr.stamme</td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td><em class="lg_mat">stuorráin</em></td><td><em class="lg_mat">stuorráiguin</em></td></tr>
<tr><td>  </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuoribuin, stuorábuin</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuoribuiguin, stuorábuiguin</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Superlativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuorimusain, stuorámusain</em></td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuorimusaiguin, stuorámusaiguin</em></td></tr>
</table> 

</section>

<section>
<title>Essiv</title>
<p> er tilstandskasus som ofte gir betydningen "som":</p>
<p><em class="lg_mat">Mun dovden iežan 'jallan'.</em></p>  
<p> <em class="lg_mat">Son gáttii mu 'boarráseabbon'.</em> </p>  
<p><em class="lg_mat">Oahpaheaddji rámpui mu 'viššaleamosin'</em>.</p> 
<p>Det er ikke forskjell på entall og flertall.</p>

<table>
<tr><td colspan="3"><strong>ESSIV</strong> Skravert: svakt stadium</td></tr>
<tr><td class="fatbottom small"><strong>stammetype</strong></td><td class="fatbottom small"><strong>grad</strong></td><td class="fatbottom"><strong>entall / flertall</strong></td></tr>
<tr><td class="small">Likest.stamme</td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td><em class="lg_mat">nuorran</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuorabun</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Superlativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">nuoramussan</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábálažžan</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td><em class="lg_mat">dábáleabbon, dábálabbon, dábálaččabun</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="fatbottom"> </td><td class="fatbottom small">Superlativ</td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">dábáleamosin, dábálamosin, dábálaččamussan</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="small">Likest.stamme</td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">linisin</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td><em class="lg_mat">litnáseabbon, litnásabbon</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="fatbottom"> </td><td class="fatbottom small">Superlativ</td><td class="fatbottom"><em class="lg_mat">litnáseamosin, litnásamosin</em></td></tr>
<tr><td class="small">Kontr.stamme</td><td class="small">Positiv</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuorisin</em></td></tr>
<tr><td>  </td><td class="small">Komparativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuoribun, stuorábun</em></td></tr>
<tr><td> </td><td class="small">Superlativ</td><td class="lightshadow"><em class="lg_mat">stuorimussan, stuorámussan</em></td></tr>
</table> 

</section>


  </body>
</document>





 
