<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>About the pedagogical project</title>
  </header>

  <body>
    <p>The project is financed by the Norwegian Sámi Parliament (405.000 NOK) and the Faculty of Humanities at the University of Tromsø. The work was initiated during the summer of 2007, and it is scheduled to be ready at the end of 2008.</p>
    <p>The project has two main goals:</p>
    <ol>
    <li>Build programs so that students and pupils may practice their communicative Sámi skills</li>
    <li>Make interactive games for Sámi.</li>
    </ol>
    <p>In our opinion, it is natural to integrate other resources from the university's Giellatekno-project in this project. Therefore, we have made the OAHPA web portal.</p>
    
<section>  
<title>Interactive practice of communication skills</title> 
    <p>The core idea of the project is to use automatic word and sentence analysis, in order to build programs that, together with the user, may interact in dialogues on everyday topics. The program may be an important addititon to pupils and students studying Sámi, but also to parents and others with some knowledge of Sámi, but with a feeling that the knowledge needs improvement. They will be able to practice the use of Sámi, and at the same time get some guidance. The program will be available on the internet, free for use for all.</p>

<p>The program also contains a lexicon with appr 100.000 words, among them appr. 40.000 names. The name lexicon makes it possible to build exercises where pupils may learn names and how to inflect them.</p>
</section>  

<section>  
<title>Interactive grammar games</title> 

<p>The way we make interactive games for Sámi, is to adjust sámi sentences and integrate them in <code>VISL</code> Visual Interactive Syntax Learning-programs. With these games, the user practices grammar skills, such as knowledge of parts of speech and sentence analysis. VISL was originally made for Danish students, but now it is used by pupils in elementary and secondary schools in both Denmark and Norway.</p>
</section>

<section>  
<title>Target group</title> 

<p>The target group consists of students and pupils, but also the pupils' parents. Internet access is available in most homes, thus parents may, either alone or together with the children, train their Sámi skills by the help of the games or by chatting with the program. The user himself chooses the topic, the program builds a dialogue on the basis of the topic, and the user's responses. The program evaluates verb declension and case usage, and tells the user what s/he has done wrong. The program can also mimic real conversations, because an answer can, to a certain degree, have an impact on the next question. If, for instance, the user answers that she/he has a dog, then the next questions can be about the dog.
</p>
</section> 

<section> 
<title>The linguistic background</title> 

<p><strong>The language technology group at the UiT</strong> has since the year 2000 made analysis programs for a.o. North Sámi, programs with which it is possible to analyse and build wordforms for Sámi text, and resolve contextual disambiguities.</p>

<p><strong>The project workers are:</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Lene Antonsen, pedagog and linguist</li> 
<li>Biret Ánne Bals Baal, linguist</li> 
<li>Saara Huhmarniemi, programmer</li>
<li>Kjellaug Isaksen, graphical designer</li>
<li>Trond Trosterud, computational linguist</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>The VISL group at Syd-Dansk Universitet in Odense</strong> uses the same computational tools as we do (finite-state transducers and constraint grammar), and with them they have build a whole suite of pedagogical programs for using the analysed texts in different ways. In this way, it is possible to add new languages to the same framework, by basically adding analysed texts to a ready-made framwork. The VISL pages now contain pedagogical games for almost 30 different languages.</p>

</section> 
<p class="last_modified" >Last changed: $Id: intro.xml,v 1.8 2005/06/21
	12:13:53 boerre Exp $
                </p>
  </body>
</document>
