<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Welcome to the OAHPA! portal!</title>
  </header>

  <body>
    <p>The Universitety of Tromsø makes pedagogical programs for learning North Sámi. We hope to eventually be able to offer the programs for Lule Sámi and South Sámi as well.</p>

    <p>Some of the links are in parenthesis. This indicates that the beta version is still not ready, but you may in any case read about our plans for it here.</p>

    <p><strong>The OAHPA! programs</strong> are made for language learning, and they are made at the University of Tromsø. The programs are scheduled to be ready at 31.12.2008. For of the programs are ready for testing. The OAHPA! programs are: </p>
 <ul>
      <li><a href="numra.eng.html">NUMRA</a> - numbers</li>
      <li><a href="leksa.eng.html">LEKSA</a> - word quiz</li>
      <li><a href="morfa.eng.html">MORFA</a> - word inflection</li>
      <li><a href="vasta.eng.html">VASTA</a> - question answering</li>
      <li><a href="sahka.eng.html">(SAHKA)</a> - dialogues</li>
    </ul> 

    <p><strong>The VISL programs</strong> are made in order to learn grammar, and they are better suited for people who already know Sámi. The VISL group at Syd-Dansk Universitet is responsible for the technique, and the University of Tromsø has added North Sámi content. The programs are:</p>
 <ul>
      <li><a href="Paintbox_eng.html">PAINTBOX</a><a href="Labyrinth_eng.html">LABYRINTH</a><a href="Shooting_eng.html">SHOOTING GALLERY</a><a href="WordFall_eng.html">WORDFALL</a> - parts of speech game</li>
      <li><a href="Syntris_eng.html">SYNTRIS</a><a href="SpaceRescue_eng.html">SPACERESCUE</a><a href="cealkkamuorraravvagat.eng.html">CEALKKAMUORRA</a> - for sentence analysis</li>
      <li><a href="Killerfiller_eng.html">KILLERFILLER</a> - provide the sentences with correct wordforms</li>
      <li><a href="animalquiz.eng.html">ANIMAL QUIZ</a> - guess the correct animal (requires good knowledge of Sámi)</li>
    </ul>     
    
    
    <p><strong>Teaching resources</strong> include generation of inflectional paradigms, dictionary, word- and text analysis, and articles treating parts of speech and sentence analysis.</p>


<p><strong>Our goal</strong> is to make it possible for the users to train everyday language. The basis for this is a set of words used in beginners' education, cf. the Oahpa-vocabulary page. But we may also make teaching material for special themes, e.g. Sámi handicraft. Contact us if you have suggestions or special needs! </p>

    <p>Some of the resources are <strong>beta-versions</strong>, which means that they may contain errors, and that there is a potential for improvement. We are indeed open to comments! (oahpa@hum.uit.no) </p>
     

      <p><a href="techspec.eng.html">Technical spesifications and links</a></p>

      <p><a href="resurssat.eng.html">Resources on other sites</a></p>

      <p><a href="birra.eng.html">About the project</a></p>
      <p class="last_modified" >
                </p>
                     <p class="last_modified" >Last changed: $Id$
                </p>    

  </body>
</document>
