<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Sahka - ready for testing</title>
  </header>

  <body>
  <p><a href="sahka.nno.html">Norsk tekst</a></p>
  <p><a href="sahka.html">Sámegillii</a></p>
  
    <p>The Sahka game consists of interactive dialogues. You may "talk to the machine". The goal is to practice verb declension, case usage, and to expand the vocabulary. You may answer the questions in different ways, but since the goal is to practice your grammar you should be prepared to answer with the same verb as the one used in the question. In yes/no questions, for example, you should not answer with only <em>in</em>. Cf.</p>
    
    <p><code>Jugat go gáfe? Gal mun jugan. / In juga.</code></p>
    
    <p>We also have open questions. To these we may attach a word list (e.g. a restaurant menu or a drawing), or you may answer freely, but with the word in the correct case. e.g.</p>
    
     <p><code>Masa don liikot buoremusat? Liikon lákcagáhkkui/njálgáide/...</code></p>
  
<p>Often the next question will come as a result of your answer to the previous one, e.g.</p> 

    <p><code>Lea go dus biila? Mus lea.</code></p>
    <p><code>Makkár biila dus lea? Mus lea Toyota Jaris.</code></p>

    
    <p>The program will above all direct your attention to errors in inflection, orthography or case usage.</p>


        <p><strong>The dialogues are:</strong></p>

    <ul>
      <li>- Oahpásmuvvan (Ordinary questions about personal matters). There are four variants - you can chat with an adult woman (Káre), an adult man (Hánsa), a boy (Lemet) or a girl (Lisá).</li>
      <li>- Guossis (Here you can practice dual verb inflection ("moai") and locative og illative. At the end of the dialogue, also accusative.)</li>
      <li>- Borramušgávppis (Practice accusative.)</li>
      <li>- Veardideapmi rámbuvrris (Adjective comparison.)</li>
     </ul>
     
         <p>We are also planning these dialogues:</p>
    <ul>     
      <li>- Gávpogii (Adverbs, postpositions)</li>
      <li>- Mátkkošteapmi (Illative, locative, comitative, time expressions.)</li>
      <li>- Jahki ja vahkku (Auxiliary verb, time expressions.)</li>
    </ul>
<p>  </p>    
<p>        <a href="http://oahpa.uit.no/oahpa/sahka"><strong>Link til Sahka</strong></a>  </p>

        <p class="last_modified" >Last changed: $Id: intro.xml,v 1.8 2005/06/21
	    12:13:53 boerre Exp $
                </p>  </body>
</document>

