<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Sahka - not ready yet</title>
  </header>

  <body>
    <p>The Sahka game consists of interactive dialogues. You may "talk to the machine". The goal is to practice verb declension, case usage, and to expand the vocabulary. You may answer the questions in different ways, but since the goal is to practice your grammar you should in e.g. yes/no questions be prepared to answer with the same verb as the one used in the question, thus not answer only by <em>in</em>. Cf.</p>
    
    <p><code>Jugat go gáfe? Gal mun jugan. / In juga.</code></p>
    
    <p>We also have open questions. To these we may attach a word list (e.g. a restaurant menu or a drawing), or you may answer freely, but with the word in the correct case. e.g.</p>
    
     <p><code>Masa don liikot buoremusat? Liikon lákcagáhkkui/njálgáide/...</code></p>
  
<p>Often the next question will come as a result of your anwer to the previous, e.g.</p> 

    <p><code>Lea go dus biila? Mus lea.</code></p>
    <p><code>Makkár biila dus lea? Mus lea Toyota Jaris.</code></p>

    
    <p>The program will above all direct your attention to errors in inflection, orthography or case usage. If you make the same mistake over and again, the program may invite you to the exercise room, in order to practice for example illative. You may also go directly to the inflection room, cf. the link to <em>Morfa</em> to the left.</p>

    <p>In some dialogues you will practice particular grammatical constructions. In other dialogues we emphasise words and expressions. Our goal is to provide a way of training Sámi which is as natural as possible.</p>
    
        <p>Users have different backgrounds, both wrt. age and dialect. Therefore you will in some cases get the opportunity to choose with whom to talk. The identity of the virtual dialogue partner functions as a variable, Káre will e.g. be an adult woman from Kárášjohka, using the local dialect, talking about topics relevant to her. Heaika will have other interests and another dialect, since we model him as a boy from Guovdageaidnu.</p>

        <p>Below you may see what dialogues we have started to make, the list will be expanded. We are open to new suggestions! We plan to have a beta version of the dialogues ready in the early autumn of 2008.</p>

    <ul>
      <li>Oahpásmuvvan (Verbs in present, habitive, expressions...)</li>
      <li>Guossis (Verbs in present, sg, du, pl...)</li>
      <li>Gávpogii (The basis is Tromsø. Focus on: adverbs, postpositions, verbs in present...)</li>
      <li>Bivttasgávppis (in the shop, comparision of adjectives...)</li>
      <li>Mátkkošteapmi (travelling, illatiiva, lokatiivva, komitatiiva...0)</li>
      <li>Jahki ja vahkku (time, auxiliaries, time expressions...)</li>


    </ul>
    <p class="last_modified" >Last changed: $Id: intro.xml,v 1.8 2005/06/21
	    12:13:53 boerre Exp $
                </p>  </body>
</document>

