<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"/usr/local/forrest/main/webapp/resources/schema/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>SpaceRescue (function game)</title>
  </header>
  <body>
  <p><a href="http://beta.visl.sdu.dk/visl/sme/edutainment/games/spacerescue.php">SpaceRescue VISL direct link</a></p>

<section>
<title>Begin to play</title>
<ol>
<li>Write the sentence cod – or</li>
<li>just press "Play".</li>
</ol>
<p>Activate the Java window and press the F2 key on your keyboard.</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>Sentence code</title>
<p>The SpaceRescue game works with sentence functions.</p>
<p>You may choose a sentence set or a specific set by typing its code, e.g. SMEA143.
In that case you may not register your result. The sentence sets are
SMEA, SMEB ja SMEC.</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>Playing</title>
<p>The sentence becomes visible. The bad octopuses are watching the words. Your goal is to rescue the sentence constituents and give them names. The game has three phases.</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>1. phase</title>
<p>You start out with five jet fighters which you can steer with the arrow keys. My may shoot at the octopuses with laser if you press the space key. You are supposed to shoot down all octopuses watching the word belonging to the same constituent. If you shoot agenst an octopyussy not belonging to the constituent in question, all the octopuses will shoot at you and try to destroy your jet fighter.You then have to move your fighter in order to protect it.</p>
<p><img alt="spacerescueimage" src="images/spacerescue.png" /></p>
</section>
<section>
<title>2. phase</title>
<p>When you have rescued a sentence constituent, you send a rescue ship on order torescue it. You only have 10 rescue ships. If you send a rescue ship too early (before you have freed a whole phrase) the octopuses may destroy the rescue ship.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>3. phase</title>
<p>When you have rescued a sentence constituent, you must choose the appropriate function (subject, verbal etc.) - the list may be found in the right margin of the game. you move upward with the <strong>A key</strong>, and downward with the <strong>D key</strong>. When you have marked the function you press the <strong>S key</strong>.</p> 
<p>If you have chosen the right function, the rescue ship flies the sentence constituent and put it in the right place, together with the function. The sentence contituent turns green.</p>
<p>If you have choosen the wrong function, the octopuses will attack you and destroy your green shield. Each sentence constituent you have rescued has two red shields - one over and one under the constituent. This means ou have two possibilities for choosing the right function. If you make the wrong choice twice, the rescue ship will be destroyed. Then the computer shows the right function, and the constituent turns red.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>Buttons and their use</title>
<p><img alt="spacerescuemeny image" src="images/spacerescuemeny.gif" /></p>


<ul>
<li><strong>arrows</strong> used to move the rescue ship.</li>
<li><strong>space bar</strong> used to shoot with the laser.</li>
<li><strong>A</strong> ("Ascend"): move up to the right function.</li>
<li><strong>D</strong>("Descend"): move down to the right function.</li>
<li><strong>S</strong>("Send"): send the right function with the rescue ship.</li>
<li><strong>R</strong>("Rescue"): send the resuce ship.</li>
</ul>

</section>


<section>
<title>Points</title>
<p>You get 10 point for each word you have associated with the right sentence function. When the whole sentence is assigned to appropriate functions, the amount of points is doubled. If you try to include words not associated with the constituent in question, you lose 5 points. The octopuses may shoot at you if ou err.  move the fighter with the <strong>arrows</strong> in order for the octopuses not to hit you.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>New sentence</title>
<p>When you are done, you may press <strong>R</strong> and get a new sentence. Then the rescue ship will send the complited sentence out in space and bring you an new sentence instead.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>The menu line</title>
<p>On the <strong>Game</strong> menu yo may stop the game by choosing "Stop Game". The game results is shown via "Highscore". This function can be chosed only before you start playing, or after you are done.</p>
<p>On the <strong>Settings</strong> menu you may turn off the sound, or turn it on again, with the "Sound effects" option. </p>
<p>Advices are found under the <strong>Help</strong> menu under "Introduction". You may also choose "Toturial" and get just that.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>Syntactic functions and their abbreviations</title>
<p>We use the following sentence functions:</p>
<table>
<tr><td><strong>Abbreviation</strong></td><td><strong>Constituent</strong></td><td><strong>Example</strong></td></tr>
<tr><td><strong>S</strong></td><td>Subject</td><td><em>Min nieiddat </em> leat čeahpit. Bahádahkki <em> son </em> lea! De dáhpáhuvai, <em>ahte rievvár bođii.</em></td></tr>
<tr><td><strong>P</strong></td><td>Verbal</td><td>Min nieiddat<em> leat </em> čeahpit.<em> Ale mana!</em> Don <em>galggat</em> jaska <em>veallát</em>.</td></tr>
<tr><td><strong>Od</strong></td><td>Object</td><td>Bija<em>  buori dola</em>.<em> Maid</em>  Máret áigu oastit? Dieđát go <em>goas mis lea čoahkkin?</em></td></tr>
<tr><td><strong>A</strong></td><td>Adverbial</td><td>Lávvui gullá<em>  maid </em> uvssot. Doai leahppi<em>  áŋgirit </em> lohkan sámegiela<em>  olles dálvvi</em>. Nieida lei<em>  skuvllas</em>. <em>Jus dieđášin</em>, de dajašin.</td></tr>
<tr><td><strong>HAB</strong></td><td>Habitive</td><td><em>Mus </em> leat ustibat.<em> Min bussás </em> leat alit čalmmit.</td></tr>
<tr><td><strong>fC</strong></td><td>Predicative</td><td>Min bussás leat<em>  alit čalmmit</em>. Gáttis ledje<em> olbmot</em>.</td></tr>
<tr><td><strong>Cs</strong></td><td>Subject predicative</td><td>Min nieiddat leat<em>  čeahpit</em>. </td></tr>
<tr><td><strong>Co</strong></td><td>Object predicative</td><td>Son oaččui dan<em>  luoikkasin</em>. Gáhkuid son ráhkada<em>  hui buriid</em>.</td></tr>
<tr><td><strong>Cp</strong></td><td>Predicative predicative</td><td>Mus leat gieđat<em>  nu galbmasat</em>.</td></tr>
<tr><td><strong>CO</strong></td><td>Coordinator</td><td><em> Muhto </em> Parkera gal deavččastetne.</td></tr>
<tr><td><strong>SUB</strong></td><td>Subordinator</td><td><em>Jus</em> dieđášin,<em>  de  </em>dajašin. Son lea viššaleabbo<em>  go </em> mun.</td></tr>
<tr><td><strong>PART</strong></td><td>Particle</td><td>Boađát<em>  go </em> odne?</td></tr>
<tr><td><strong>VOC</strong></td><td>Vocative</td><td><em>Gilette,  </em> boađe donge!</td></tr>
</table>

<p>We use the following embedded functions:</p>

<table>
<tr><td><strong>Abbreviation</strong></td><td><strong>Bálddalasti lahttu</strong></td><td><strong>Example</strong></td></tr>
<tr><td><strong>CO</strong></td><td>Coordinator</td><td>Sii ráhkadedje muohtaádjáid<em>  ja</em> muohtaeŋgeliid.</td></tr>
<tr><td><strong>CJT</strong></td><td>Conjunct </td><td>Sii ráhkadedje<em>  muohtaádjáid</em> ja<em>  muohtaeŋgeliid</em>.</td></tr>
</table>
</section>

<section>
<title>Help functions and SpaceRescue link</title>

<p>If you want to learn more about syntactic functions: 
<a href="cealkkalahtut.eng.html">Syntactic functions</a></p>

<p>... or you may want to practice: 
<a href="cealkkacoavdinmuorra.eng.html">syntactic tree building</a></p>

<p><a href="http://beta.visl.sdu.dk/visl/sme/edutainment/games/spacerescue.php">VISL SpaceRescue link</a></p>
</section>
<p class="last_modified" >Last changed: $Id$
                </p>
</body>
</document>