<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>WordFall</title>
  </header>

  <body>
  <section>
    <title>WordFall</title>
    <p>In the WordFall game you work with parts of speech. The game presents a sentence, and the word falls down, one by one. Via the arrows you may assign the correct POS to each falling word. If you press the down arrow, the word will fall quicker. The game is, in short, a Tetris game.</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>Begin to play</title>
<ol>
<li>Write a sentence code, or - to get a random sentence -</li>
<li>just press "Play"</li>
</ol>
<p>Activate the Java window with the arrow key, and press the F2 key to start the game.</p>
<p><img alt="Wordfall-image" src="images/wordfall2.jpg" /></p>

</section>
<section>
<title>Sentence code</title>
<p>ou may choose sentence type or a specific sentence by typing in a sentence code, say <code>SMEA143</code>.
If you do this, you will not be able to register your results in the player hall-of-fame. The sentence codes are:
<code>SMEA, SMEB</code> and <code>SMEC</code> + a number for each sentence.</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>Points</title>
<p>You get 10 points each time you find the right POS. If you assign a word to the wrong POS, you loose 5 points. If you are able to do the whole sentence without errors, you get 10 bonus points for each word, or you double your point score!</p>

<p>To the right of the sentence window you find the Penalty Box. Each time a word get the wrong CVS, the box will be filled with more water. When the Penalty Box is full, there will come a brick wall, making the distance to travel for new words shorter. When the brick wall covers the whole window, the game is over. You may also quit the game by pressing  "Quit Game" on the menu.</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>Results</title>
<p>If your result belongs to the top-10 of today, or is within the overall top-100, you may register your name, country and home place in the hall of fame list.</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>The levels</title>
<p>are "Beginner", "Intermediate" and "Expert". The higher level you choose, the longer are the sentences and the faster the words fall. The brick walls are also bigger, and the window is filled faster. The default level is "Intermediate", but you may choose your appropriate level on the menu.</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>Parts of speech</title>
<p>If you do not want to use all parts of speech, you may choose "Word Classes" in the "Game" menu. There you may either choose a predefined set, or via "Custom" choose a subset which suits you. Note that you then are not allowed to register your results.</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>Stop the game</title>
<p>Game-menyas don válljet "Stop Game" dahje "Quit". Muhto don beasat registreret bohtosa dušše jus válljet "Stop Game", ja jus dus leat doarvái čuoggát.</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>Jietna</title>
<p>Don sáhtát jáddadit jiena "Sound Effects Settings"-menyas.</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>Statistihkka</title>

<p>Go speallu nohká, de dihtor čájeha dutnje bohtosiid, ja jearrá háliidatgo
hárjehallat daid sátneluohkáid mat ledje váddásepmosat dutnje.</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>Sátneluohkát</title>
<p>Mii geavahit dáid sátneluohkáid:</p>

<table>
<tr><td>n   </td><td>substantiiva (<em>girji, lohkamat, golmmas</em>)</td></tr>
<tr><td>prop   </td><td>propra (namma) (<em>William, Kárášjohka</em>)</td></tr>
<tr><td>pron </td><td>pronomena (<em>mun, sidjiide, soapmásat, ollu</em>)  </td></tr>
<tr><td>num </td><td>lohkosátni (<em>okta, 1923</em>)           </td></tr>
<tr><td>adj </td><td>adjektiiva (<em>alit, ollu, njealját</em>)                     </td></tr>
<tr><td>prp</td><td>Preposišuvdna/postposišuvdna (<em>alde, miehtá</em>) </td></tr>
<tr><td>conj</td><td>konjunkšuvdna (<em>ja, ahte, vaikko</em>)            </td></tr>
<tr><td>intj</td><td>interjekšuvdna (<em>vuoi, jippi</em>)                </td></tr>
<tr><td>adv </td><td>advearba (<em>hui, johtilit, olgun</em>)             </td></tr>
<tr><td>v   </td><td>vearba (<em>lean, borran, juhkamis</em>)             </td></tr>
<tr><td>part   </td><td>partihkal (<em>go, amma, han</em>)             </td></tr>

</table>
<p>Muhtun sajis leat merkejuvvon sátneluohkát mat eai gávdno sámegielas, nugo "infm" (infinitiivamearka) ja "art" (artihkal).</p>
<p>Don sáhtát lohkat eanet min cealkagiid birra ja sátneluohkáid birra dás: <a href="cealkkamuorraravvagat.html">Cealkagat, cealkkalahtut ja sátneluohkát</a>
</p>

</section>
<section>
<title>WordFall-liŋka</title>
<p><a href="http://beta.visl.sdu.dk/visl/sme/edutainment/games/wordfall.php">WordFall VISL</a></p>
</section>
<p class="last_modified" >Last changed: $Id: intro.xml,v 1.8 2005/06/21
	12:13:53 boerre Exp $
                </p></body>
</document>
