<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Noun derivation</title>
  </header>

  <body>

    <p>
      <a href="noun-intro.rus.html"> По-русски </a> | <em>In English</em> |
      <a href="noun-intro.fin.html"> Suomeksi </a> |
      <a href="noun-intro.nob.html"> På norsk </a>
    </p>

<p><em class="focus">NORSK OVERSETTELSE AV DENNE SIDEN ER UNDER ARBEID.</em></p>

    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Noun derivation is a process with which you can easily expand your vocabulary. By taking
        adjectives, nouns or verbs and combining them with certain suffixes you can create new nouns
        with a meaning affiliated to that of the original word. Take te adjective <em class="lg_mat"
          >viõlggâd</em> 'white' as an example: By adding a suffix we can form the abstract noun <em
          class="lg_mat">viõlggâdvuõtt</em> 'whiteness'.</p>

      <p>The derived nouns are declined in cases, just as other nouns are. The case endings are
        added after the derivational suffix.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Denominal nouns</title>
      <p>We will start by explaining how to form new nouns out of already existing ones. By doing
        this, you can achieve a slight change in meaning. To make it clearer, let us have a look at
        the example noun <em class="lg_mat">põrtt</em> 'house'. With the help of derivational
        suffixes we can create new nouns which are in some way connected to the original word:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">põõrtâž</em> 'small house'</li>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">põrttneˊǩǩ</em> 'farm (house) owner'</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Note that some derivationalal suffixes are attached to the strong, other to the weak stem
        of a noun.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The Diminutive</title>
      <p>The diminutive is generally used to express that something is small. However, in Skolt
        Saami, as in many other languages, it also used for expressing endearment or intimacy. In
        order to form the diminutive of a noun, we need to add the suffix <em class="lg_mat"
          >-âž</em> or <em class="lg_mat">-až</em> to the weak stem of the noun:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">piânnai</em> 'dog' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">piânnǥaž</em> 'small
          dog'</li>
        <li>
          <em class="lg_mat">põrtt</em> 'house' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">põõrtâž</em> 'cottage, i.e.
          small house'</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Diminutives are also frequently used with names:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">Mäˊrjj</em> 'Mary' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">Määˊrjjaž</em> 'little Mary'
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>You also have to bear in mind that words with palatalisation can lose this in the
        diminutive:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">kueˊll</em> 'fish' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">kuâlaž</em> 'little
          fish'</li>
      </ul>

      <p>All diminutive nouns belong to the same inflectional class and are declined according to
        class IX nominals.</p>
      <p>Click here to see a fully inflected noun of this paradigm.<!--LINK--></p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Personalisation</title>
      <p>The next suffix, <em class="lg_mat">-neˊǩǩ</em>, is very useful if you want to express how
        a person is affiliated with something. So, if you know the word 'art', this suffix will help
        you to form the word 'artist'. The suffix is not only used to express a person who practices
        a certain activity but can also be used to express that someone lives in a certain place or
        owns something. But let us look at the examples so that it becomes clearer:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">põrtt</em> 'house' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">põrttneˊǩǩ</em> 'farm
          owner'</li>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">Âˊvvel</em> 'Ivalo' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">âˊvvelneˊǩǩ</em> 'resident
          of Ivalo'</li>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">njuhččâm</em> 'tongue' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">njuhččâmneˊkk</em>
          'gossipmonger, telltale' </li>
      </ul>
      <p>This suffix is very useful because, unlike in other languages where you need to learn
        various endings to denote nationality depending on the word, (just look at Norwegian: <em
          class="lg_mat">italiener</em> for 'Italian', <em class="lg_mat">nordmann</em> for
        'Norwegian' and <em class="lg_mat">svenske</em> for 'Swede') you can take practically any
        place name or country and easily express that you are talking about its inhabitants by
        simply adding this suffix. The same is true for owners and performers of something.</p>
      <p>However, you have to bear in mind that some irregularities might occur when using this
        suffix:</p>
      <p>Here we can see that the collective ending <em class="lg_mat">-õs</em> was lost before
        inserting the personalising suffix.</p>
      <ul>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">čeäppõs</em> 'art' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">čeäppneˊkk</em> 'artist'</li>
      </ul>
      <p>This example is very unusual as the second syllable is omitted. This is generally not the
        case for disyllabic words:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">Jaapan</em> 'Japan' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">jaapneˊkk</em> 'Japanese
          person'</li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Abstraction</title>
      <p>The suffix <em class="lg_mat">-vuõtt</em> is used to give an abstract meaning to the
        original word. This means you can use it when you want to talk about a general concept
        behind something. To make it easier to understand, just remember our first example:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">viõlggâd</em> 'white' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">viõlggâdvuõtt</em>
          'whiteness'</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Generally, this suffix is only added to adjectives and nouns:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">naˊzvaan</em> 'friend' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">naˊzvaanvuõtt</em>
          'friendship'</li>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">puärraz</em> 'parents' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">puärrazvuõtt</em>
          'parenthood'</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The new nouns belong to the first inflectional class, but be careful because only the
        suffix undergoes stem gradation as it forms a new stress group:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">na´zvaanvuõtt</em> ➞ <em class="lg_mat">na´zvaanvuõđ</em> (PL. NOM) ➞
            <em class="lg_mat">na´zvaanvuõ´tˊte</em> (SG.ILL)</li>
      </ul>
      <p>☞ Note the change from strong, to weak to overlong grade within the derivational suffix.
        Click here to see a fully inflected noun of this paradigm.<!--LINK--></p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Deverbal nouns</title>
      <p> Now we will talk about how to form nouns out of verbs. First of all, when you have
        selected your verb, you need to get rid of the infinitival ending. The infinitival ending is
        the last vowel plus "d" at the end of the uninflected form. This means the verb is not
        inflected for person (e.g. I, you, he/she/it).</p>
      <p>To make it clearer, we will look at the example of <em class="lg_mat">laauǥõõttâd</em> 'to
        bathe'.</p>

      <p>Now we delete the infinitival ending (in this case <em class="lg_mat">-âd</em>) and get <em
          class="lg_mat">laauǥõõtt</em>. With this form as the base, we can express a slightly
        different meaning of the word by simply adding suffixes:</p>

      <ul>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">laauǥõõtt-i</em> 'bather; i.e. a person that bathes'</li>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">laauǥõõtt-mõš</em> 'the bathing, i.e. the process of bathing'</li>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">laauǥõõtt-õs</em> 'the bath'</li>
      </ul>

      <p>☞ Note that when deleting the infinitival ending of verbs that contain an overshort vowel,
        the vowel will be fully realised in this form: </p>
      <ul>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">juurdčed</em> 'to think' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">jurdčumuš</em>
          'thinking, reasoning' </li>
      </ul>
      <p>But let us have a look at the various suffixes one by one below.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Action Nominalisation</title>
      <p>The suffix <em class="lg_mat">-mõš</em> is used to turn a verb denoting some kind of change
        in state into a noun. This means you can form a noun out of a verb and therefore name a
        process, like:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">põõllâd</em> 'to fear' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">põõllmõš</em> '[the
          process of] fearing'</li>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">seillad</em> 'to be preserved' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">seillmõs</em>
          '[the process of] conservation'</li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Agent Nominalisation</title>
      <p>The suffix <em class="lg_mat">-i</em> is also used to denote a noun, however, it denotes
        the agent. This means that with the help of this suffix you can express who is performing
        the action of the original verb. To make it clearer we shall have a look at some
        examples:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">uˊvdded</em> 'to give' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">uˊvddi</em> 'giver, i.e.
          person who gives'</li>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">njiimted</em> 'to breastfeed' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">njiimteei</em>
          'wet nurse, i.e. person who breastfeeds'</li>
      </ul>
      <p>These nouns are declined according to the inflectional paradigm of class IV nouns. Click
        here to see a fully inflected noun of this paradigm<!--LINK-->.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>General Nominalisation</title>
      <p>The next derivational suffix we will talk about is <em class="lg_mat">-õs</em>. This suffix
        is used a lot in Skolt Saami as it brings about a general nominalisation.</p>
      <ul>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">vuäˊpsted</em> 'to instruct' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">vuäˊpstõs</em>
          'instructions'</li>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">šõddâd</em> 'to grow' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">šâddõs</em> 'growth'</li>
      </ul>
      <p>☞ Notice that this suffix can also be used with compounds, i.e. words where two or more
        words were previously joined together to form a new single entity:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">teäˊǧǧ</em> 'money' <em class="lg_mat">ruõkkâd</em> 'to save' ➞ <em
            class="lg_mat">teäˊǧǧruõkkâd</em> 'to save money' (lit. 'to moneysave') ➞ <em
            class="lg_mat">teäˊǧǧruõkkõs</em> 'fund'</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Contrary to <em class="lg_mat">-mõš</em>, the suffix <em class="lg_mat">-õs</em> does not
        describe the process of doing something (See <em class="lg_mat">laauǥõõtt-mõš</em> 'the
        bathing' and <em class="lg_mat">laauǥõõtt-õs</em> 'the bath').</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Omission of Verbal Ending (Conversion)</title>

      <p>To make it even easier, we can also form nouns by simply omitting the infinitival ending of
        a verb. In this case, no additional ending is needed. This phenomenon is called
        zero-derivation or conversion.</p>
      <ul>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">tuejjeed</em> 'to do' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">tuejj</em> 'deed,
          act'</li>
      </ul>
      <p>However, there are a few things you have to bear in mind when using this suffix.</p>
      <p>. First, verbs from group A which, as you might recall, usually have stem vowels from the
        high group, will now change towards the low variant:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">kuullâd</em> 'to hear' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">kooll</em> 'hearing'</li>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">põõllâd</em> 'to fear' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">pââll</em> 'fear'</li>
      </ul>

      <p> ☞ Note the vowel change from <em class="lg_mat">–u–</em> ➞ <em class="lg_mat">–o–</em> and
          <em class="lg_mat">–õ–</em> ➞ <em class="lg_mat">–â–</em> here. For a list of the
        corresponding high and low vowel pairs, click here.<!--LINK--></p>

      <p>Furthermore, the palatalisation of group A and C verbs is lost:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">tieˊtted</em> 'to know' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">teâtt</em>
          'knowledge'</li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Multiple deriviations</title>

      <p> ☞ Note that you can add more than one derivational suffix to a word. Just look at this
        example:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">njiimted</em> 'to breastfeed' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">njiimteei</em>
          'wet nurse'</li>
      </ul>

      <p>In this example you can see that the stem of the word has already undergone derivation, in
        this case the causative marker <em class="lg_mat">–t</em> was added before the infinitival
        ending:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">njiimâd</em> 'to suck' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">njiimted</em> 'to
          breastfeed'.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The same is true for our example from above, <em class="lg_mat">laauǥõõttâd</em> 'to
        bathe'. In this case the original word was already awarded a reflexive meaning by inserting
        the derivational suffix <em class="lg_mat">–õõtt</em> before the stem:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">laauǥed</em> 'to wash' ➞ <em class="lg_mat">laauǥõõttâd</em> 'to
          bathe'</li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <p>These were the most important and mostly used derivational endings and rules for noun
      derivation in Skolt Sámi. They can help you form new nouns out of already existing words.</p>

    <p>Here you can read more about <a href="noun-intro.eng.html">nouns in general</a>
      <!-- and <a href="noun-inflexion.eng.html">noun
        inflexion</a>-->. </p>

    <p>Back to the <a href="grammar.eng.html">grammar main page</a>. </p>

  </body>
</document>
