<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
<header>
<title>Алфавит и произношение – Введение</title>
</header>

<body>
<p>
<em>По-русски</em> | <a href="pronounciation-intro.eng.html">In English</a> | <a
href="pronounciation-intro.fin.html">Suomeksi</a> | <a href="pronounciation-intro.nob.html">På norsk</a>
</p>

<p>Обратно на главную страницу<a href="grammar.rus.html">грамматики</a>. </p>

<p><em class="focus">ПОЛНЫЙ ПЕРЕВОД ДАННОЙ СТРАНИЦЫ ПРОИЗВОДИТЬСЯ В НАСТОЯЩИЙ МОМЕНТ.</em></p>

<p>На страницу <a href="alphabet.rus.html">Алфавит</a> найдете список всех колтта-саамских букв. У
каждой буквы можно слышать как произносится. На других страниц мы обьяснаем произношение всех букв
для <a href="pronounciation-vowel.rus.html">гласных</a>, <a href="pronounciation-consonant.rus.html"
>согласных</a> и других <a href="pronounciation-sign.rus.html">знаков</a> при помощи примерних слов. </p>

<!--
<p>We are also writing a small <a href="../lesson-intro.rus.html">textbok</a> which is linked to
pages with <a href="../exercise-intro.rus.html">exercises</a>, among other thinks. </p>
-->

<p>The Skolt Sámi orthography uses Latin letters and is relatively close to the actual
pronounciation. Therefore, only in a few cases we need to use a kind of simplyfied transkription.
These are the forms written in between two slashes / … /. This transcription shall only give you an
impression about the general pronounciation of the respective letter, but does not show the actual
Skolt Sámi orthography! </p>

<p>Our materials comply with the orthography which is official in Finland. This orthography is also
used in Norway today. </p>

<p>Please note that our explanations are written for people without special knowledge in phonology.
We compare the Skolt Sámi pronounciation with Russian and in some cases with other languages in order
to create easily comprehensible explanations. Better phonological descriptions you will find in the
following sources: </p>

<ul>
<li>Feist, T. 2010: <em>A grammar of Skolt Saami</em>. Manchester.</li>
<li>Korhonen, M. / Mosnikoff / Sammallahti, P. 1973: <em>Koltansaamen opas</em>. Helsinki</li>
<li>Moshnikoff, S. / Moshnikoff J. / Koponen, E. 2009: <em>Koltansaamen koulukielioppi</em>.
Inari.</li>
</ul>

<p>Remember that stress normally falls on the first syllable in Skolt Sámi. </p>

</body>
</document>
