<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
<header>
<title>Aakkosto ja ääntäminen – Johdatus</title>
</header>

<body>
<p>
<a href="pronunciation-intro.rus.html">По-русски</a> | <a href="pronunciation-intro.eng.html">In
English</a> | <em>Suomeksi</em> | <a href="pronunciation-intro.nob.html">På norsk</a>
</p>

<p><em class="focus">TÄTÄ SIVUA OLLAAN KÄÄNTÄMÄSSÄ SUOMEKSI.</em></p>

<p>Back to the <a href="grammar.fin.html">grammar's main page</a>. </p>

<p>On the page <a href="alphabet.fin.html">Alphabet</a> you find a list with all Skolt Sámi letters.
For each letter you can also listen to the general pronunciation. On the following pages, the
pronunciation of each letter for <a href="pronunciation-vowel.fin.html">vowels</a>, <a
href="pronunciation-consonant.fin.html">consonants</a> and other <a
href="pronunciation-sign.fin.html">letter-like signs</a> is explained with the help of example words
you can listen to. </p>

<!--
<p>We are also writing a small <a href="../lesson-intro.fin.html">textbok</a> which is linked to
pages with <a href="../exercise-intro.fin.html">exercises</a>, among other thinks. </p>
-->

<p>Remember that Skolt Sámi has several letters which Finnish does not have. Apart from that, Skolt
Sámi orthography is relatively close to the actual pronunciation. Therefore, only in a few cases we
need to use a kind of simplyfied transkription. These are the forms written in between two slashes /
… /. This transcription shall only give you an impression about the general pronunciation of the
respective letter, but does not show the actual Skolt Sámi orthography! </p>

<p>Please note that our explanations are written for people without special knowledge in phonology.
We compare the Skolt Sámi pronunciation with Finnish and in some cases with other languages in order
to create easily comprehensible explanations. Better phonological descriptions you will find in the
following sources: </p>

<ul>
<li>Feist, T. 2010: <em>A grammar of Skolt Saami</em>. Manchester.</li>
<li>Korhonen, M. / Mosnikoff / Sammallahti, P. 1973: <em>Koltansaamen opas</em>. Helsinki</li>
<li>Moshnikoff, S. / Moshnikoff J. / Koponen, E. 2009: <em>Koltansaamen koulukielioppi</em>.
Inari.</li>
</ul>

<p>Remember that stress normally falls on the first syllable in Skolt Sámi, just like in Finnish. </p>

</body>
</document>
