<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
<header>
<title>Alphabet and pronunciation – Intro</title>
</header>

<body>
<p>
<a href="pronunciation-intro.rus.html">По-русски</a> | <em>In English</em> | <a
href="pronunciation-intro.fin.html">Suomeksi</a> | <a href="pronunciation-intro.html">På norsk</a>
</p>

<p>Back to the <a href="grammar.eng.html">main page of the grammar</a>. </p>

<p>On the page <a href="alphabet.eng.html">Alphabet</a> you can find a list of all Skolt Sámi letters and you can listen to the general pronunciation of each letter. On the following pages, the pronunciation of each letter for <a href="pronunciation-vowel.eng.html">vowels</a>, <a
href="pronunciation-consonant.eng.html">consonants</a> and other <a
href="pronunciation-sign.eng.html">letter-like characters</a> is explained with the help of example
words. </p>

<!--
<p>We are also writing a small <a href="../lesson.eng.html">textbok</a> which is linked to pages
with <a href="../exercise.eng.html">exercises</a>, among other things. </p>
-->

<p>Remember that the pronunciation of some letters in Skolt Sámi are different than in English. 
Furthermore there are several letters which English does not have. Apart from that, Skolt Sámi
orthography is relatively close to the actual pronunciation. Therefore, only in a few cases do we need
to use a kind of simplified transcription. These are the forms written in between two slashes / … /.
Our simplified transcription should only give you a general impression of the pronunciation of the respective
letter, but does not show the actual Skolt Sámi orthography! </p>

<p>Our materials comply with the orthography used officially in Finland. The same norm is now also
used in Norway and Russia. </p>

<p>Please note that our explanations are written for students without special knowledge in
phonology. We only compare the Skolt Sámi pronunciation with Norwegian and Russian and in some cases
with other languages in order to create easily comprehensible explanations. Better phonological
descriptions can be found in the following sources: </p>

<ul>
<li>Feist, T. 2010: <em>A grammar of Skolt Saami</em>. Manchester.</li>
<li>Korhonen, M. / Mosnikoff / Sammallahti, P. 1973: <em>Koltansaamen opas</em>. Helsinki</li>
<li>Moshnikoff, S. / Moshnikoff J. / Koponen, E. 2009: <em>Koltansaamen koulukielioppi</em>.
Inari.</li>
</ul>

<p>Remember that stress normally falls on the first syllable in Skolt Sámi, just like in other Sámi
languages or in Finnish. </p>

</body>
</document>
