<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Verb derivation</title>
  </header>

  <body>

    <p>
      <em> По-русски </em> | <a href="verb-derivation.eng.html">In English</a> | <a
        href="verb-derivation.fin.html"> Suomeksi </a> | <a href="verb-derivation.nob.html"> På
        norsk </a>
    </p>

    <p><em class="focus">ПЕРЕВОД ДАННОЙ СТРАНИЦЫ ПРОИЗВОДИТЬСЯ В НАСТОЯЩИЙ МОМЕНТ.</em></p>

    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Derivation is a process with which you can easily expand your vocabulary. By taking
        adjectives, nouns or verbs and combining them with certain suffixes you can create new verbs
        with a meaning affiliated to that of the original word. Take te adjective <em class="lg_mat"
          >xxx</em> 'xxx' as an example: By adding a suffix we can form the xxx verb <em
          class="lg_mat">xxx</em> 'xxx'.</p>

      <p>The derived verbs are declined in infinite or finite forms, just as other verbs are. The
        inflectional endings are added after the derivational suffix.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Deverbal verbs</title>
      <p>We will start by explaining how to form new verbs out of already existing ones. By doing
        this, you can achieve a slight change in meaning. To make it clearer, let us have a look at
        the example verb <em class="lg_mat">xxx</em> 'xxx'. With the help of derivational suffixes
        we can create new verbs which are in some way connected to the original word:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">xxx</em> 'xxx'</li>
        <li><em class="lg_mat">xxx</em> 'xxx'</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Note that some derivational suffixes are attached to the strong, other to the weak
        consonant stem of a verb.</p>
    </section>

    <p>These were the most important and mostly used endings and rules for verb derivation in Skolt
      Sámi. They can help you form new verbs out of already existing words.</p>

    <p>Here you can read more about <a href="verb-intro.rus.html">verbs in general</a>
      <!-- and <a href="verb-inflexion.eng.html">verb
        inflexion</a>-->. </p>

    <p>Back to the <a href="grammar.rus.html">grammar main page</a>. </p>

  </body>
</document>
