<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>A language learning program for Plains Cree</title>
  </header>

  <body>
  
  <p></p>

    <p><a href="http://testing.oahpa.no/crk_oahpa/">Oahpa</a> is a learner's aid for acquisition of languages with complex grammar, like Plains Cree. The programs make tasks for the students, and they can be integrated in course materiales, like we have done for North and South Saami, e.g. <a href="http://kursa.oahpa.no">North Saami Language courses for students</a>. The programs have many choices and therefore can be adapted to the students' level and needs. The teacher can give links to the students which include the relevant settings. Here is a brief introduction to each of the programs which are included in the Plains Cree demo: </p>
<p><strong>Numra</strong> - practice with numbers, dates, clock and money. Practice from number to word, or from word to number. Examples:</p> 
<ul>
<li>nîstanaw nistosâp - 23</li>
<li>nîstanaw cipahikanis pâmayes nisto tipahikan - 10:20</li>
<li>5 ehakimiht opiniyâwewowipîsimohk - 5th of May</li>
<li>nîso newopehikanak - $2.50</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Leksa</strong> - practice with words, from Cree to English/French, or from English/French to Cree. One can include audiofiles. In the demo there are audiofiles for some of the words: Choose audiofiles in the book menu.</p>
<p><strong>Morfa S</strong> - inflection of nouns and verbs, individual words</p>
<p><strong>Morfa C</strong> - inflection of nouns and verbs in context (question + answer)</p>

<p>Be aware of that the demo is only a start, a fully developed program will include much more tasks. The tasks should be made in collaboration with teachers.</p> 
<p>The student can limit the vocabulary to what is given in the textbooks or the curriculum. In Leksa-program s/he can choose semantic field instead of book.</p>
<p>For all programs:</p>
<ul>
<li>The student can try as many times as s/he wants, before s/he asks for the key</li>
<li>The student can ask for hints, and then try again (not implemented yet)</li>
<li>There will be links to grammar explanations (not implemented yet)</li>
<li>The tasks are generated from programs, which make thousands of different tasks</li>
<li>It is possible to make to program in two versions, one for each alphabet: Romans and syllables</li>
<li>It is possible to adapt the program to variants (dialects, different spelling conventions), and make a menu for it.</li>
<li>In a fully developed program, there can be a 'login'. The teacher can log in and see which tasks the students have been working with, and the students can follow their own progression compaired to the curriculum.</li>
</ul>


<p>The name Oahpa is a North Saami word for: Learn! This name and the names of each program can be changed to names, which sound better for the Cree students.</p> 
<p>The idea behind the programs, is that if the students can practice grammar alone, and still get immidiate response to their work, then the teacher can spend more of the time in the class to practice other parts of the language skills. </p>



  </body>
</document>
