<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>


  <messages xml:lang="eng"> 
    <!-- Feedback about declination paradigms. -->
    <message order="A" id="hard_m_inanim">WORDFORM is a hard stem masculine inanimate noun. It has the same endings as теа́тр.</message>
    <message order="A" id="hard_m_anim">WORDFORM is a hard stem masculine animate noun. It has the same endings as студе́нт.</message>
    <message order="A" id="soft_m_inanim">WORDFORM is a soft stem masculine inanimate noun. It has the same endings as рубль.</message>
    <message order="A" id="soft_m_anim">WORDFORM is a soft stem masculine animate noun. It has the same endings as медве́дь.</message>
    <message order="A" id="m_inanim_k">WORDFORM is a masculine inanimate noun ending in -к, -г, or -х. It has the same endings as уро́к.</message>
    <message order="A" id="m_anim_k">WORDFORM is a masculine animate noun ending in -к, -г, or -х. It has the same endings as учени́к.</message>
    <message order="A" id="m_inanim_sh">WORDFORM is a masculine inanimate noun ending in -ж, -ч, -ш, or -щ. It has the same endings as каранда́ш.</message>
    <message order="A" id="m_anim_sh">WORDFORM is a masculine animate noun ending in -ж, -ч, -ш, or -щ. It has the same endings as борщ.</message>
    <message order="A" id="m_inanim_ts">WORDFORM is a masculine inanimate noun ending in -ц. It has the same endings as огуре́ц.</message>
    <message order="A" id="m_anim_ts">WORDFORM is a masculine animate noun ending in -ц. It has the same endings as оте́ц.</message>
    <message order="A" id="m_inanim_j">WORDFORM is a masculine inanimate noun ending in -й. It has the same endings as музе́й.</message>
    <message order="A" id="m_anim_j">WORDFORM is a masculine animate noun ending in -й. It has the same endings as геро́й.</message>
    <message order="A" id="m_inanim_ij">WORDFORM is a masculine inanimate noun ending in -ий. It has the same endings as санато́рий.</message>
    <message order="A" id="m_anim_ij">WORDFORM is a masculine inanimate noun ending in -ий. It has the same endings as вика́рий.</message>
    <message order="A" id="m_anim_anin">WORDFORM is a masculine animate noun in -анин. It has the same endings as датча́нин.</message>
    <message order="A" id="m_anim_jonok">WORDFORM is a masculine animate noun in - ёнок/-онок. It has the same endings as цыплёнок.</message>
    <message order="A" id="hard_m_inanim_pl_a">WORDFORM is a hard stem masculine inanimate noun with NPl -á. It has the same endings as сви́тер.</message>
    <message order="A" id="soft_m_inanim_pl_ja">WORDFORM is a soft stem masculine inanimate noun with NPl -я́. It has the same endings as я́корь.</message>
    <message order="A" id="hard_m_anim_pl_a">WORDFORM is a hard stem masculine animate noun with NPl -á. It has the same endings as дире́ктор.</message>
    <message order="A" id="soft_m_anim_pl_ja">WORDFORM is a soft stem masculine animate noun with NPl -я́. It has the same endings as учи́тель.</message>
    <message order="A" id="hard_f_inanim">WORDFORM is a hard stem feminine inanimate noun. It has the same endings as ко́мната.</message>
    <message order="A" id="hard_f_anim">WORDFORM is a hard stem feminine animate noun. It has the same endings as ма́ма.</message>
    <message order="A" id="soft_f_inanim">WORDFORM is a soft stem feminine inanimate noun. It has the same endings as ба́ня.</message>
    <message order="A" id="soft_f_anim">WORDFORM is a soft stem feminine animate noun. It has the same endings as герои́ня.</message>
    <message order="A" id="f_inanim_ka">WORDFORM is a feminine inanimate noun ending in -кa, -гa, or -хa. It has the same endings as кни́га.</message>
    <message order="A" id="f_anim_ka">WORDFORM is a feminine animate noun ending in -кa, -гa, or -хa. It has the same endings as соба́ка.</message>
    <message order="A" id="f_inanim_sha">WORDFORM is a feminine inanimate noun ending in -жa, -чa, -шa, or -щa. It has the same endings as ка́ша.</message>
    <message order="A" id="f_anim_sha">WORDFORM is a feminine animate noun ending in -жa, -чa, -шa, or -щa. It has the same endings as касси́рша.</message>
    <message order="A" id="f_inanim_tsa">WORDFORM is a feminine inanimate noun ending in -цa. It has the same endings as у́лица.</message>
    <message order="A" id="f_anim_tsa">WORDFORM is a feminine animate noun ending in -цa. It has the same endings as учи́тельница.</message>
    <message order="A" id="f_inanim_Vja">WORDFORM is a feminine inanimate noun ending in a vowel (other than и) +-я. It has the same endings as ста́туя.</message>
    <message order="A" id="f_anim_Vja">WORDFORM is a feminine animate noun ending in a vowel (other than и) +-я. It has the same endings as фе́я.</message>
    <message order="A" id="f_inanim_ija">WORDFORM is a feminine inanimate noun ending in -ия. It has the same endings as ле́кция.</message>
    <message order="A" id="f_anim_ija">WORDFORM is a feminine animate noun ending in -ия. It has the same endings as фу́рия.</message>
    <message order="A" id="f_inanim_b">WORDFORM is a feminine inanimate noun ending in -ь. It has the same endings as дверь.</message>
    <message order="A" id="f_anim_b">WORDFORM is a feminine animate noun ending in -ь. It has the same endings as фотомоде́ль.</message>
    <message order="A" id="f_inanim_shb">WORDFORM is a feminine inanimate noun ending in -жь, -чь, -шь, or -щь. It has the same endings as ночь.</message>
    <message order="A" id="f_anim_shb">WORDFORM is a feminine animate noun ending in -жь, -чь, -шь, or -щь. It has the same endings as мышь.</message>
    <message order="A" id="hard_n">WORDFORM is a hard stem neuter noun. It has the same endings as сло́во.</message>
    <message order="A" id="hard_n_anim">WORDFORM is a hard stem neuter noun. It has the same endings as ча́до.</message>
    <message order="A" id="soft_n">WORDFORM is a soft stem neuter noun. It has the same endings as мо́ре.</message>
    <message order="A" id="n_ko">WORDFORM is a neuter noun ending in -кo, -гo, or -хo. It has the same endings as бла́го.</message>
    <message order="A" id="n_ishshe">WORDFORM is a neuter noun ending in -ище. It has the same endings as жили́ще.</message>
    <message order="A" id="n_anim_ishshe">WORDFORM is a neuter animate noun ending in -ище. It has the same endings as чудо́вище.</message>
    <message order="A" id="n_tse">WORDFORM is a neuter noun ending in -це. It has the same endings as со́лнце.</message>
    <message order="A" id="soft_n_ije">WORDFORM is a soft stem neuter noun ending in -ие. It has the same endings as рожде́ние.</message>
    <message order="A" id="n_bje">WORDFORM is a neuter noun ending in -ье/-ьё. It has the same endings as здоро́вье.</message>
    <message order="A" id="n_mja">WORDFORM is a neuter noun ending in -мя. It has the same endings as вре́мя.</message>
    <message order="A" id="adj_ending">This noun has the same endings as an adjective.</message>
    <message order="A" id="papa">This noun is masculine, but looks like a hard stem feminine animate noun. It has the same endings as ма́ма.</message>
    <message order="A" id="djadja">This noun is masculine, but looks like a soft stem feminine animate noun. It has the same endings as герои́ня.</message>
    <message order="A" id="indeclinable_noun">This noun is does not change its form.</message>
    <message order="A" id="irregular_noun">This is an irregular noun.</message>õ
    <!-- Feedback about stress. -->
    <message order="B" id="stress_stem">This noun always has stress on the stem.</message>
    <message order="B" id="stress_ending">This noun always has stress on the ending.</message>
    <message order="B" id="stress_ending_except_ISg">This noun has stress on the ending in all forms except the ISg.</message>
    <message order="B" id="stress_stem_sg_stress_ending_pl">This noun has stress on the stem in the singular and on the ending in the plural.</message>
    <message order="B" id="stress_ending_sg_stress_stem_pl">This noun has stress on the ending in the singular and on the stem in the plural.</message>
    <message order="B" id="stress_ending_sg_stress_stem_ASg_pl">This noun has stress on the ending in the singular, but on the stem in the accusative singular and in the plural forms.</message>
    <message order="B" id="stress_stem_sg_NPl_APl">This noun has stress on the stem in the singular, nominative plural and accusative plural, but has stress on the ending in the other plural forms.</message>
    <message order="B" id="stress_stem_sg_NPl">This noun has stress on the stem in the singular and nominative plural, but has stress on the ending in the other plural forms.</message>
    <message order="B" id="stress_ending_except_NPl">This noun has stress on the ending in all forms except the nominative plural.</message>
    <message order="B" id="stress_ending_except_ASg_NPl">This noun has stress on the ending in all forms except the accusative singular and nominative plural.</message>
    <message order="B" id="stress_ending_except_ISg_NPl">This noun has stress on the ending in all forms except the instrumental singular and the nominative plural.</message>
    <!-- Feedback about special features. -->
    <message order="C" id="mobile_vowel">This noun has a mobile vowel.</message>
    <message order="C" id="GPl_ej">This noun has genitive plural -ей.</message>
    <message order="C" id="no_GPl">This noun has no genitive plural form.</message>
    <message order="C" id="loc2">This noun has a second locative form.</message>
    <message order="C" id="gen2">This noun has a second genitive form.</message>
</messages>

    