<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>Sámi dialogue based language learning system: Design
    document</title>
  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <p></p>

      <section>
        <title>Architecture Overview</title>

        <p>The software consists of Dialogue manager, Sentence parser and
        Speller together with suggestion mechanism. In addition, user Feedback
        and Tutorial section are integrated to the dialogue. The software is
        used via web interface.</p>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Component Design</title>

      <p>The heart of the system is the dialogue manager. It conducts the
      dialogue by selecting the next utterance made by the machine. It reacts
      to the user's replies and starts feedback and tutorial dialogues when
      needed. Dialogue manager calls sentence parser and speller to parse the
      user replies.</p>

      <section>
        <title>Sentence parser</title>

        <p>The system is able to parse sentences, also incorrect ones. At the
        moment, there is an analyzator and disambiguator and we are able to
        get full syntactic analysis of the sentences that belong to the
        language.</p>

        <p>The parser process involves three steps: check against predefined
        set of correct answers, speller and grammar check. First of all, each
        question has a predefined set of answers that can be generated
        beforehand. If the answer does not belong to the set of predefined
        answers, the sentence is sent to speller. If the words in the
        utterance are not recognized, the problematic word receives
        suggestions. When all the words are recognized, the predefined set of
        answers is checked again. If that check fails, the utterance is sent
        to the analyzer. In this final step, the sentence undergoes either
        overall grammar check or there is more fine-grained check where the
        type of the question is taken into account. We have to decide which
        one. The two classes of errors, spelling errors and grammatical errors
        are described in more detail separate sections.</p>

        <section>
          <title>Spelling errors</title>

          <p>Spelling errors are recognized by the speller. Speller suggests
          an alternative, or a list of alternatives, from where the user
          selects the correct one. Suggestion mechanism is restricted.</p>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Grammatical errors</title>

          <p>Grammatical errors are words in wrong forms. Grammatical analysis
          should be such that the words receive an analysis although they
          belong to an ungrammatical sentence.</p>

          <p>There are two classes of grammatical errors: question-specific
          errors and common errors. <strong> Question-specific errors
          </strong> are the type where the user is expected to use some
          pronoun. For example, if the question is "Jugatgo gáfe?", then the
          user should use first person singular in the answer, both in the
          pronoun and the verb form. Does the question always determine the
          grammatical form of the answer, or do we need a general class of
          grammatical errors?</p>

          <p>Each question is paired with a list of correct answers that
          involve the same verb as in the question (see the dialogue section
          below). However, if we want to allow the user to use also other
          verbs than what is provided in the question, the correct grammatical
          information that is expected has to be specified somehow. I don't
          know how this should be done. Usage of syntactic information
          etc.</p>

          <p><strong>Common errors </strong>could be deteceted in sentences
          that do not belong to the predefined set of answers for the
          question. I.e. basic grammar checking. Each grammatical error has a
          type. For example, if a sg1 subject is paired with a verb in wrong
          form, we may ask the user to change the verb form. The errors are
          classified and the actions they cause are stored in an xml-structure
          which is described below, in the tutorial section.</p>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Feedback and tutorial</title>

        <p>The system gives feedback about spelling errors and grammatical
        errors. See the section speller for spelling errors. Whenever a
        grammatical error is detected, a feedback window and the tutorial
        section are activated. Feedback may be more fine-grained than
        tutorial. One suggestion for the format is described below. You may
        decide the classes of feedback as you like, this example just
        illustrates the xml-structure. Note that the individual feedback may
        be more fine-grained than the tutorial.</p>

        <source>feedback.xml

&lt;error type="MAINV_SG1"&gt;
  &lt;fb&gt;Select a verb in first person singular.&lt;/fb&gt;
  &lt;tut type="verb_inflection"/&gt;
&lt;/error&gt;
..
&lt;error type="MAINV_PL1"&gt;
  &lt;fb&gt;The pronoun "we" requires first person plural for the verb form.&lt;/fb&gt;
  &lt;tut link="verb_inflection"/&gt;
&lt;/error&gt;

&lt;error type="incomplete_answer"&gt;
  &lt;fb&gt;Answer with complete clauses.&lt;/fb&gt;
  &lt;tut link="complete_clauses"/&gt;
&lt;/error&gt;</source>

        <p>The tutorial section consists of longer sections of text that
        describe certain grammatical phenomenon. They are attached only to
        grammatical errors (since we don't have any mechanism to detect the
        type of spelling error). Each type of grammatical error has its own
        tutorial section, which can be opened when an error is
        encountered.</p>

        <source>tutorial.xml

&lt;tut name="verb_inflection"&gt;
..text and explanations with examples and formatting..
&lt;/tut&gt;</source>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Dialogue context</title>

        <p>The dialogue system in this program is machine-governed, which
        means that machine asks questions, user answers and the machine
        commentes upon the answers before it carries on. The conversation may
        also involve questions posed by the user, but the type of questions is
        defined by the machine. In the first version, we will have only
        questions asked by the machine. The dialogue system consists of two
        parts: dialogue context and dialogue manager.</p>

        <p>When the program starts, the user first selects the conversation he
        wants to try. In addition, he may select some grammatical properties
        he wants to practice. Since the language learning system concentrates
        on learning the verb inflection, the grammatical properties would be
        Tense and Person-Number. Perhaps others as well. When the grammatical
        properties are selected (e.g. Present and Sg1), the questions are
        formatted so that at least some of them expect answer in the form
        selected by the user (Present and Sg1).</p>

        <p>The context can be selected from a list of dialogues. In the later
        versions, there may be dialogues based on a picture, etc. The
        dialogues may be planned for different common situations that involve
        interaction: shopping, cafe etc., or by taking into account user's
        interests and age for example. All the utterances made by the program
        are prepared beforehand.</p>

        <p>Dialogue context consists of a list of topics that may be included
        in the conversation. When the user selects some conversation, the
        topics are selected and the conversation is generated. The list of
        questions may split to branches if the conversation contains yes/no
        -questions that are used as a selection criteria for the next
        questions. When all the questions in the branch are used, a new topic
        is selected.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Dialogue manager</title>

        <p>Dialogue manager selects the next utterance based on the dialogue
        context and user input. In the simplest dialogues, there is only one
        route through the dialogue. The program asks a question from the user
        and the user replies. To create a feeling of a conversation, the next
        question is based on the user input whenever possible.</p>

        <section>
          <title>Selecting the next question</title>

          <p>There are two types of questions: yes/no questions and
          wh-questions. In addition, there are questions that have a fixed
          answer, such as "How are you?". The yes/no questions create branches
          to the conversation, where the next utterance by the machine depends
          on the user answer. The selection must be done reliably, therefore
          each question is stored together with a list of probable affirmative
          answers and a list of probable negative answers.</p>

          <p>For example, the question "Jugatgo gáfe?" is paired with two
          lists of possible answers:</p>

          <source>  affirmative: Jugan, Mun jugan, De jugan, Juo, mun jugan
  negative: In juga, In juga gáfe, In juga maidege</source>

          <p>If the user input is one of these, then the next question can be
          selected reliably on the basis of the answer. Otherwise, the next
          question is selected following the discourse context. We could think
          of some heuristics here, for example if the answer starts with "Juo"
          then we conclude that the sentence is affirmative even though it was
          not listed in the set of answers and similarly with the negation
          verb. However, then there is a chance to do false predictions, for
          example if the user enters "Yes, but.." In the first prototype, the
          selection will be based on a preformatted list of answers.</p>

          <p>Also, we want to be able to change the format of the question so
          that instead of asking in Sg2, the question could be in Pl2 or Du2
          for example. This means that the example above is too simplistic.
          The question should be paired with the morphological information.
          The conversation may be selected so that the same form is used in
          most of the questions.</p>

          <source>  Juotteko kahvia?
  aff: Juomme, Kyllä juomme, kyllä, juomme kahvia, kyllä, me juomme kahvia.
  neg: Emme juo, Emme juo kahvia</source>

          <p>Therefore, the question could be formed using the base form or,
          alternatively, the morphological information alone. The form may be
          given either straight in the xml-structure or it can be generated.
          There may also be alternative questions for one question type to get
          variability to the conversation. Since there may be variability at
          least in the Person-Number and perhaps also otherwise, we have to
          find some general format for the questions. Let's start with a
          simple yes/no question.</p>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Specifying a general form for a yes/no -question and its
          answers</title>

          <p>The idea is that the question may be represented using very
          general terms. This way, we may vary the grammatical properties of
          sentences, for example Tense and Person-Number. When the user
          selects the Tense and Person-Number he likes, the questions are
          generated accordingly. Some questions may be more restricted, but
          that's fine. I would like to include the possibility to use both
          very general format for the question and more specific where the
          utterances and questions made by machine are explicitely stated. We
          will use the same names for tags and tagsets that are defined in
          korpustags.txt.</p>

          <source>&lt;question name="jugatgo_gáfe"&gt;
  &lt;q Tense="Prs" PN="Sg2"&gt;Jugatgo gáfe?&lt;/q&gt;
  &lt;q Tense="Prs" PN="Sg2"&gt;Jugatgo gáfe?&lt;/q&gt;
  ...
&lt;/question&gt;

&lt;question name="jugatgo_gáfe"&gt;
  &lt;q&gt;&lt;grammar V="juhkat" N="gáffe"&gt;V+MV_GRAM+Qst N+Sg+Acc&lt;/grammar&gt;&lt;/q&gt;
&lt;/question&gt;

&lt;grammar type="MV_GRAM"&gt;
  &lt;tag&gt;V+Ind+Tense+PersonNumber&lt;/tag&gt;
&lt;/grammar&gt;</source>

          <p>Or, it is possible to use even more general types of questions.
          For example (these are only examples, you may define the tag classes
          as you like):</p>

          <source>&lt;question name="jugatgo_gáfe"&gt;
  &lt;q type="go_objsg"&gt;&lt;grammar V="juhkat" N="gáffe"/&gt;&lt;/q&gt;
&lt;/question&gt;

&lt;proto_question type="go_objsg"&gt;
  &lt;q&gt;V+MV_GRAM+Qst N+SG+ACC&lt;/q&gt;
&lt;/proto_question&gt;</source>

          <p>This formulation allows the properties of verb to be parametrized
          and selected by the program (or the user when he selects the
          grammatical properties he wants to practice).</p>

          <p>When the question are in general format, we would like the
          answers have the similar format. In this case, the verb and object
          are recieved from the program so it doesn't have to be specified
          again. Nevertheless, if the question can be answered using different
          verbs, then a list of verbs can be provided.</p>

          <source>&lt;answer name="jugatgo_gáfe"&gt;
  &lt;aff&gt;
    &lt;ans&gt;V+MV_GRAM&lt;/ans&gt;
    &lt;ans&gt;Pron V+MV_GRAM&lt;/ans&gt;
    &lt;ans&gt;De V+MV_GRAM&lt;/ans&gt;
    &lt;ans&gt;Juo, Pron V+MV_GRAM&lt;/ans&gt;
  &lt;/aff&gt;
  &lt;neg&gt;
    &lt;ans&gt;Neg+NEG_GRAM V+CONNEG&lt;/ans&gt;
    &lt;ans&gt;Neg+NEG_GRAM V+CONNEG N+SG+ACC&lt;/ans&gt;
    &lt;ans&gt;Neg+NEG_GRAM V+CONNEG maidege&lt;/ans&gt;
  &lt;neg&gt;
&lt;/answer&gt;</source>

          <p>Or, we may abstract words like "De" and "Juo" away and provide
          them by the program, so that an answer to a yes/no question may
          start with "De" or "Juo" and only what follows is parsed. It is also
          possible to mark optionality straight in the input:</p>

          <source>&lt;proto_answer type="go_objsg"&gt;
  &lt;aff&gt;
    &lt;ans&gt;(Pron) V+MV_GRAM (N+SG+ACC)&lt;/ans&gt;
  &lt;/aff&gt;
  &lt;neg&gt;
    &lt;ans&gt;Neg+NEG_GRAM V+CONNEG (N+SG+ACC)&lt;/ans&gt;
  &lt;neg&gt;
&lt;/proto_answer&gt;</source>

          <p>The idea is that these protoquestions and protoanswers can always
          be overridden by more specific questions and answers. For example it
          is possible to write down the question and answers in the exact
          forms without any variation. This more specific format can be used
          by specifying the name of it in the dialogue.</p>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>The dialogue structure</title>

          <p>Each conversation is stored in an xml-document that has e.g. the
          format below. The conversation consists of topics. Each topic
          contains an unordered list of questions. Each yes/no questions may
          contain three elements that contain the instructions for different
          actions: affirmative, negative and default action. Action may be an
          utterance or a link to the next question. The default action is used
          if none of the other actions are not activated. If there is no
          action at all, next topic is selected. Regardless of how the
          conversation proceeds, there may be opening or ending statements for
          both the conversation and the topic.</p>

          <source>&lt;conversation name="cafe"&gt;
 &lt;topic name="juhkat"&gt;
   &lt;opening&gt;Mitä joisimme?&lt;/opening&gt;
   &lt;question name="jugatgo_gáfe"&gt;
     &lt;aff&gt;
       &lt;q link="sokeri"/&gt;
       &lt;q link="maito"/&gt;
     &lt;/aff&gt;
     &lt;neg&gt;
       &lt;q link="jugatgo_deaja"/&gt;
       &lt;q link="jugatgo_maidege"/&gt;
     &lt;/neg&gt;
     &lt;default&gt;
       &lt;q link=".."/&gt;
     &lt;/default&gt;
   &lt;/question&gt;

   &lt;question name="sokeri"&gt;
     &lt;q&gt;Otatko sokeria?&lt;/q&gt;
     &lt;aff&gt;
       &lt;utt&gt;Ole hyvä!&lt;/utt&gt;
     &lt;/aff&gt;
     &lt;default&gt;
      &lt;q link="maito"/&gt;
     &lt;/default&gt;
   &lt;/question&gt;

 &lt;/topic&gt;

 &lt;topic name="syöminen"&gt;
  ..
 &lt;/topic&gt;

 &lt;topic name="maksaminen.."&gt;
  ..
 &lt;/topic&gt;
...
&lt;/conversation&gt;</source>

          <p>This xml-structure does not contain the selection criteria for
          affirmative and negative answers but they are in separate document.
          In this way, the questions can also be reused in different
          conversations.</p>

          <p>In the case of wh-questions, the next question is selected
          following the discourse context. The topic of the conversation can
          be changed partly randomly. However, in some cases the user input
          could conduct the conversation e.g. if the user mentions a topic
          that is listed in available topics. For example "Maid don jugat?"
          and we have prepared a conversation regarding that topic (tea,
          coffee). In the first versions, we will not have this
          functionality.</p>

          <p>In addition, there is a list of answers that may be cause
          different kind of reactions. For example, incomplete answers cause
          feedback in all the conversations:</p>

          <source>&lt;error link="incomplete_answer"&gt;
  &lt;ans&gt;In&lt;/ans&gt;
  &lt;ans&gt;Juo&lt;/ans&gt;
&lt;/error&gt;</source>

          <p>Some answers may cause tutorial window to open etc. The structure
          of feedback and tutorial is described in the section below.</p>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Speller</title>

        <p>Speller for North and Lule Sámi will be used in correcting spelling
        errors by the user.</p>

        <section>
          <title>Suggestion mechanism</title>

          <p>The suggestion mechanism can be restricted by having
          conversation-based lexicons, which contain thematically restricted
          vocabularies. On the other hand, the whole project needs a lexicon
          of common words that may occur in each dialogue (containing
          pronouns, auxiliaries, common verbs,..) It may even turn out that
          one restricted lexicon is suitable for all the discussions.</p>

          <p>There is one problem: If the user tries to write the correct
          grammatical form of a verb, but has a spelling error, the speller
          may suggest grammatically wrong form.</p>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Web interface</title>

        <p>The system is accessed via web interface. When the user selects the
        conversation, it is generated, and the topics are selected and put in
        some order. Thus the conversation is ready when the user starts it.
        The yes/no questions are taken into account when the conversation is
        generated. The wh-questions may cause topic changes that cannot be
        taken into account beforehand and require the conversation to be
        regenerated, and in addition, there has to be a logging mechanism of
        already used topics. The topic changes by the user are not included in
        the first version of the system.</p>

        <p>Spelling errors cause a small window to open which briefly states
        the error and lists the suggestions.</p>

        <p>Grammatical errors cause similar window to open, with brief
        description of the error and some assistance. In addition, the
        tutorial section in the side bar is activated and the correct tutorial
        page is opened.</p>

        <p>A risk for the program and especially for the usage of the
        interface is the speed. To avoid waiting times in case of correct
        sentences, the dialogue is generated beforehand as much as possible.
        When the user's answer is not found from the predefined set of
        answers, a speller call is required, after that there may be analyzer
        call and all of these take time. Therefore, attention has to be paid
        to the speech already at start of the development.</p>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Quality assurance</title>

      <p></p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Algorithms</title>

      <p></p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>