<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>Sámi dialogue based language learning system: Design
    document</title>
  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <p></p>

      <section>
        <title>Architecture Overview</title>

        <p></p>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Component Design</title>

      <p>Why the software is needed.</p>

      <section>
        <title>Sentence parser</title>

        <p>The system is able to parse sentences, also incorrect ones. At the
        moment, there is an analyzator and disambiguator and we are able to
        get full syntactic analysis of the sentences that belong to the
        language. Is it possible to parse also sentences which contain errors?
        There are two classes of errors: spelling errors and grammatical
        errors. The spelling errors can be recognized by the speller, which
        can suggest an alternative. (the user has to be able to select the
        alternative she wants). The grammatical errors are words in wrong
        forms. The grammatical analysis should be such that the words receive
        an analysis although they belong to an ungrammatical sentence. The
        suggestion mechanism for grammatical errors is described below.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Dialogue system</title>

        <p>The dialogue system consists of three parts: dialogue context,
        dialogue manager, and </p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Tutorial dialogue</title>

        <p>The system gives feedback and makes suggestions on the basis of
        errors produced by the user. The sentence-frames for the feedback are
        created beforehand, such as "Did you mean ___?", or "Perhaps you meant
        ___ or ___ or ?", what other frames are there?</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Sentence generator</title>

        <p>The sentence generator is part of the dialogue system. It does not
        involve any semantic representation, but the words and correct forms
        are provided by the dialogue system.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Speller</title>

        <p>Speller for North and Lule Sámi will be used in correcting spelling
        errors by the user.</p>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Quality assurance</title>

      <p></p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Algorithms</title>

      <p></p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>