<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>ICALL (Intelligent Computer-Assisted Language Learning): Research and development</title>
  </header>

  <body>
  <section>
    <title>Documentation for the different Oahpa projects</title>
    <ul>
    <li><strong>North Saami Oahpa: </strong>
     <a href="univ-oahpa.html">University Oahpa (2011-2013) – NUV-project P88/2011</a> // 
     <a href="first_oahpa_project.html">The first Oahpa project (2007-2008)</a>
    </li>
    <li><strong>South Saami Oahpa: </strong>
     <a href="sma2-oahpa.html">South Saami 2 (2012-2013)</a> //
     <a href="sma-oahpa.html">South Saami (2010-2011)</a> //     
    </li>
    <li><strong>Other Saami Oahpa versions: </strong>
     <a href="smn-oahpa.html">Inari Saami (2011-)</a> //
     <a href="sjd-oahpa.html">Kildin Saami (2012-)</a> //
     <a href="sms-oahpa.html">Skolt Saami (2012-)</a> //
    </li>
    <li><strong>Oahpa for other languages: </strong>
     <a href="rus-oahpa.html">Russian (2012-)</a></li>
   <li><a href="http://oahpa.no/">Documentation for end
    users, (teachers, pupils students)</a> </li>
    </ul>
    </section>

    <section>
    <title>Technical documentation on maintenance of the Oahpa platform</title>
        <ul>
          <li><a href="common/OahpaTechnicalDocumentation.html">Maintaining the system</a></li>
          <li><a href="common/logextraction.html">Extracting log information</a></li>
          <li>Documentation on scripts, etc. (forthcoming...)</li>
        </ul>
    </section>
    <section>
    <title>Grammar learning</title>
        <ul>
          <li>Here is coming a link about VISL</li>
        </ul>
    </section>
    <section>
    <title>Dictionaries for language learners</title>
        <ul>
          <li><a href="http://giellatekno.uit.no/doc/dicts/neahttadigisanit.html">Neattadigisánit – FST-dictionary</a> A reading comprehension dictionary combined with a morpological analysator</li>
          <li><a href="http://giellatekno.uit.no/doc/dicts/dicts.html">Other dictionaries</a></li>
        </ul>
    </section>
    <section>
    <title>Research on spelling and spell checkers</title>
        <ul>
          <li><a href="../../techdoc/proof/spelling/testing/sme/pl/goldstandard/20130412-1000-samlafil.correct.txt.summary.html">Test results for an annotated L1-corpus with both real-word og non-word errors</a></li>
        </ul>
    </section>
  <section>
    <title>Publications and presentations</title>
    <ul>
 <li>Antonsen, Lene (in press): Constraints in Free-input Question-Answering Drills. 2nd workshop on NLP for computer-assisted language learning. NoDaLiDa 2013. Linköping Electronic Conference Proceedings Volum 85.</li>
 <li>Antonsen, Lene, Ryan Johnson, Trond Trosterud, Heli Uibo (in press): Generating modular grammar exercises with finite-state transducers. 2nd workshop on NLP for computer-assisted language learning. NoDaLiDa 2013. Linköping Electronic Conference Proceedings Volum 85.</li>
 <li>Johnson, Ryan, Lene Antonsen, Trond Trosterud (in press): Using finite state transducers for making efficient reading comprehension dictionaries. Proceedings of the 19th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics.</li>
 <li>Antonsen, Lene 2013: <a href="laremidler.pdf">Samiske læremidler på internett – og UiTs rolle i dette .</a> Presentasjon på seminar for samisklærere arrangert av Utdanningsdirektoratet og Fylkesmannen i Nord-Trøndelag, Nordland, Troms og Finnmark: Vurderingskurs for sensorer for samisk som førstespråk og andrespråk i grunnskolen og videregående skole. Tromsø, 14.-15. februar 2013.</li>
 <li>Antonsen, Lene 2012: <a href="fst_approach_antonsen.pdf">Improving feedback on L2 misspellings – an FST approach.</a> Workshop on NLP for computer assisted language learning, SLTC 2012. Linköping Electronic Conference Proceedings Volum 80</li>
 <li>Antonsen, Lene 2012: <a href="saami_online.pdf">Online Saami.</a> Presentation at Arbeidsseminar om IT-undervisning i Nordens språk, 23-24.10.12 Lund.</li>
 <li>Trosterud, Trond 2012: <a href="LLLC2012_Trosterud.pres.pdf">Investigating morphological complexity by means of ICALL log data.</a> Presentation at Learner Language, Learner Corpora 5-6.10.12 in Oulu.</li>
 <li>Antonsen, Lene 2012: <a href="lenepresLLLC.pdf">Learner corpus from a free-form student response system.</a> Presentation at Learner Language, Learner Corpora 5-6.10.12 in Oulu.</li>
  <li>Antonsen, Lene, Berit A. B. Baal and Trond Trosterud 2012: <a href="poster_eurocall_2012.pdf">Letting ICALL make minority language instruction at university level available over a wide area.</a> Poster made for Eurocall 2012, in Göteborg.</li>
  <li>Antonsen, L., Huhmarniemi, S. and T. Trosterud 2009: <a href="http://hdl.handle.net/10062/9546">Interactive pedagogical programs based on constraint grammar.</a> Proceedings of the 17th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics. Nealt Proceedings Series 4.</li>
<li>Antonsen, Lene, Saara Huhmarniemi and Trond Trosterud 2009: <a href="http://dspace.utlib.ee/dspace/bitstream/10062/14287/1/antonsen_etal.pdf">Constraint Grammar in Dialogue Systems</a>. NEALT Proceedings Series 2009. Volum 8. s. 13-21.</li>
<li>Antonsen, L., Baal, B. Á. B., Huhumarniemi, S., Trosterud, T. 2009: <a href="http://brage.bibsys.no/samall/bitstream/URN:NBN:no-bibsys_brage_30823/2/Diedut_2009_1_samlet_20091015_pdfX3-2002.pdf">Dihtor ja giela válljenvejolašvuođat – gielalaš ja pedagogalaš čuolmmat. (The Computer and the Variability of Language – Linguistic and Pedagogical Issues).</a> – Johanna Ijäs – Nils Øivind Helander (doaim.), Sáhkavuoruin sáhkan. Sámegiela ja sámi girjjálašvuođa muhtin áigeguovdilis dutkanfáttát s. 87–102. Dieđut 1/2009. Guovdageaidnu: Sámi allaskuvla.</li>
  <li><a href="smaOahpaUserOrange.pdf">Oahpa hjelper deg å lære samisk.</a> Poster about South Saami Oahpa – for the language communities. Made for Gïeleviermie conference in Røros, 19-20.10.11</li>
  <li><a href="VDsmakruana.pdf">Voestes Digibaakoeh: Ordboka forstår bøyde ord.</a> Poster about South Saami dictionary – for the language communities. Made for Gïeleviermie conference in Røros, 19-20.10.11  </li>
  <li><a href="Oahpa_graffleposter4.pdf">Interactive Pedagogical Programs Based on Constraint Grammar.</a> Poster made for NODALIDA conference 16.05 2009 Odense.   </li>
  <li><a href="VD.pdf">Vuosttaš Digisánit: Ordboka forstår bøyde ord.</a> Poster made for Forskningsdagene 2009.   </li>
  <li><a href="Oahpa_forskningstorget.pdf">Lær samisk med språkteknologi.</a> Poster made for Forskningsdagene 2009.   </li>


</ul>
  </section>
  </body>
</document>

