<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Oahpa: Research and publications</title>
  </header>

  <body>
  <section>
    <title>Key papers for Oahpa</title>
    <ul>
  <li>Antonsen, L., Huhmarniemi, S. and T. Trosterud 2009: <a href="http://hdl.handle.net/10062/9546">Interactive pedagogical programs based on constraint grammar.</a> Proceedings of the 17th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics. Nealt Proceedings Series 4.</li>
<li>Antonsen, Lene, Saara Huhmarniemi and Trond Trosterud 2009: <a href="http://dspace.utlib.ee/dspace/bitstream/10062/14287/1/antonsen_etal.pdf">Constraint Grammar in Dialogue Systems</a>. NEALT Proceedings Series 2009. Volum 8. s. 13–21.</li>
    </ul>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Other publications and presentations related to Oahpa</title>
    <ul>
 <li>Antonsen, Lene 2013: <a href="http://www.ep.liu.se/ecp_article/index.en.aspx?issue=086;article=002">Constraints in Free-input Question-Answering Drills.</a> Proceedings of the second workshop on NLP for computer-assisted language learning at NODALIDA 2013, May 22-24, Oslo, Norway. NEALT Proceedings Series 17: 11-26.</li>
 <li>Antonsen, Lene, Ryan Johnson, Trond Trosterud, Heli Uibo 2013: <a href="http://www.ep.liu.se/ecp_article/index.en.aspx?issue=086;article=003">Generating modular grammar exercises with finite-state transducers.</a> Proceedings of the second workshop on NLP for computer-assisted language learning at NODALIDA 2013, May 22-24, Oslo, Norway. NEALT Proceedings Series 17: 27-38.</li>
 <li>Antonsen, Lene 2012: <a href="http://www.ep.liu.se/ecp_article/index.en.aspx?issue=080;article=001">Improving feedback on L2 misspellings – an FST approach.</a> Proceedings of the SLTC 2012 workshop on NLP for CALL, Lund, 25th October, 2012. Linköping Electronic Conference Proceedings 80: 1-10.</li>
 <li>Antonsen, Lene 2012: <a href="saami_online.pdf">Online Saami.</a> Presentation at Arbeidsseminar om IT-undervisning i Nordens språk, 23–24.10.12 Lund.</li>
<li>Antonsen, Lene, Ciprian Gerstenberger, Ryan Johnson, Trond Trosterud, Heli Uibo 2012: <a href="nudoc/multilingual_pres.pdf">A modular system for porting advanced interactive programs to new, morphology-rich languages.</a> Presentation at Eurocall 2012, in Göteborg.</li>
  <li>Antonsen, Lene, Berit A. B. Baal and Trond Trosterud 2012: <a href="poster_eurocall_2012.pdf">Letting ICALL make minority language instruction at university level available over a wide area.</a> Poster made for Eurocall 2012, in Göteborg.</li>
  <li>Antonsen, L., Huhmarniemi, S. and T. Trosterud 2009: <a href="http://hdl.handle.net/10062/9546">Interactive pedagogical programs based on constraint grammar.</a> Proceedings of the 17th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics. Nealt Proceedings Series 4.</li>
<li>Antonsen, Lene, Saara Huhmarniemi and Trond Trosterud 2009: <a href="http://dspace.utlib.ee/dspace/bitstream/10062/14287/1/antonsen_etal.pdf">Constraint Grammar in Dialogue Systems</a>. NEALT Proceedings Series 2009. Volum 8. s. 13–21.</li>
  <li><a href="smaOahpaUserOrange.pdf">Oahpa hjelper deg å lære samisk.</a> Poster about South Saami Oahpa – for the language communities. Made for Gïeleviermie conference in Røros, 19–20.10.11</li>
  <li><a href="Oahpa_graffleposter4.pdf">Interactive Pedagogical Programs Based on Constraint Grammar.</a> Poster made for NODALIDA conference 16.05 2009 Odense.   </li>
  <li><a href="Oahpa_forskningstorget.pdf">Lær samisk med språkteknologi.</a> Poster made for Forskningsdagene 2009.   </li>
</ul>
  </section>


  </body>
</document>

