<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>S치mi dialogue based language learning system: Requirements
    document</title>
  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <p>(See the plan in the application)</p>

      <section>
        <title>Purposes and objectives</title>

        <p>(See the plan in the application)</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Project team</title>

        <p>(See the plan in the application)</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Project overview, the most important features</title>

        <p>(See the plan in the application)</p>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Description of the problem</title>

      <p>Why the software is needed. General considerations of the pedagogical
      issues. Something we have to keep in mind when developing the program
      (See the plan in the application)</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Description of the software </title>

      <p>(See the plan in the application)</p>

      <section>
        <title>Features and functional capacities</title>

        <p>Table listing the features and their priority.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Other requirements</title>

        <p>Platforms, web, tools</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Usability</title>

        <p>There is a web-pased interface. Other usability considreations,
        plans for user manuals etc.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Long-term plans and maintenance</title>

        <p></p>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Prototypical conversations</title>

      <p>Examples of how the conversation could proceed.</p>

      <section>
        <title>Dialogue 1. Situation?</title>

        <ul>
          <li>Bures!</li>

          <li></li>

          <li></li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Question types</title>

      <p>What kind of questions the computer asks together with different
      types of answers. (I have only the examples we have discussed. Please
      fill in the exact list of different types of questions together with
      acceptable answers with the correct grammatical specification if it's
      clear. The details of which verb requires which kind of arguments are
      not listed here.)</p>

      <section>
        <title>go-questions</title>

        <p>Jugatgo g치fe?</p>

        <p>Different possible answers together with comments:</p>

        <ul>
          <li>Jugan.</li>

          <li>In.</li>

          <li>In juga.</li>
        </ul>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Maid-questions</title>

        <p>Maid don jugat?</p>

        <ul>
          <li>G치fe</li>

          <li></li>
        </ul>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>(Next type)</title>

        <p></p>

        <ul>
          <li></li>

          <li></li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Other resposes to the user.</title>

      <p>The other things that the computer says, like "I like coffee too",
      followed by the next question. These are described in more detail in
      each dialogue, but something general guidlines, ideas, situations where
      the computer can comment the user could be listed here.</p>

      <section>
        <title>Comment type 1.</title>

        <p>Description</p>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Tutorial dialogue</title>

      <p>(I just write here some ofmy considerations, please rewrite where
      needed) The system gives feedback and makes suggestions on the basis of
      errors produced by the user. The language of the feedback? If we have
      feedback only in S치mi, then it must be really simple (avoid grammatical
      terms). It is not difficult to do different versions of feedback for
      different languages, since the sentences that are used in feedback are
      static.</p>

      <p>The tutorial dialogue can be implemented as part of the general
      dialogue as: -What did you buy? - I buy bread. - Did you mean: You
      bought bread? (perhaps alternatives) - Yes ... Or the tutorial dialogue
      can be separate from the actual dialogue, it can be a pop-up window or
      something more pleasant: a side bar that contains the feedback, or..</p>

      <p>Are there different levels in the feedback? First, "There is a wrong
      form in the sentence the word "___" , Let's try again" If the form is
      wrong again, then provide the grammatical form where the word should be
      in "The correct form is nominative", if the user fails then give the
      correct alternatives "Perhaps you meant __ or __?".</p>

      <p>How the user responds to the feedback? Does she merely choose from
      the list or is she required to write the sentence again?</p>

      <p>The form of the feedback is created beforehand. The feedback is
      different in different situations. We probably want to "teach" the user,
      give grammatical information, reasons why the form she used is wrong,
      etc. The types of feedback have to be thought carefully. (I just add
      couple of examples, please fill in the list of feedback sentences in
      desired languages.)</p>

      <section>
        <title>Word was not recognized, there is a spelling error.</title>

        <p></p>

        <ul>
          <li>1. feedback: "Wrong word form".</li>

          <li>2. feedback: "Did you mean __?" or "Did you mean __ or __?"</li>
        </ul>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Word is recognized, but it's not in the correct form.</title>

        <p></p>

        <ul>
          <li>1. feedback: "Wrong word form".</li>

          <li>2. feedback: "The word __ is in __ form, but this sentence
          requires __ form which is __"</li>
        </ul>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>(Next type..)</title>

        <p></p>

        <ul>
          <li></li>

          <li></li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Comparison with the existing approaches</title>

      <p>(Did you find any? links and comments here)</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>