<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
	<header>
		<title>Making OAHPA! into other languages</title>
	</header>
	<body>
		<p>
This is the documentation for how to make OAHPA! work for new languages. We start with two of the programs, Leksa and Morfa-C, and the goal is to make a demo of each of them, with 50-100 lemmata.</p>
		<section>
			<title>Why do it?</title>
			<p>
her må vi ha en tekst om hva som er vitsen med å gjøre dette</p>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>For which languages?</title>
			<p>
In principle, Oahpa! can be used for any language. Compared to many other interactive learning approaches, Oahpa! is particularly will suited for languages possessing a rich morphology, and for tasks where the system accepts free-form input from the student (like in the programs Vasta and Sahka).
			</p>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Who can do it?</title>
			<p>
her må vi ha en tekst om hva som kreves av forkunnskaper etc...
lingvistisk kunnskap om språket.... en fordel å ha underviningserfaring
</p>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Leksa</title>
			<p>
Word quizes are fun, and useful in order to train the vocabulary. The Leksa game is meant for pupils who are learning a new language, perhaps also for pupils in need of writing practice. The program should accept synonyms. Leksa works in both language directions.</p>
<p><a href="http://oahpa.uit.no/"><strong>Here</strong></a>
 you can see how the North Sámi Leksa works. Choose instruction language in the right margin before you choose Leksa.
</p>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Morfa-C</title>
			<p>
The pupil may practice word inflection in a systematic way - either with singleton words (Morfa-S) or words in sentences, in order to learn the context in which to use the wordforms (Morfa-C). The student may choose part-of-speech.  We have chosen to help you to make Morfa-C because then you get Morfa-S for free if you add more lemmata (and word forms).</p>
<p><a href="http://oahpa.uit.no/"><strong>Here</strong></a> you can see how the North Sámi Morfa-S and Morfa-C work. Choose instruction language in the right margin before you choose the program. 
                
</p>
		</section>
		<p class="last_modified">Last changed: $Id: newdevelopers.xml,v 1.6 2009/09/09
	lene Exp $
				</p>
	</body>
</document>