<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
	<header>
		<title>More for developers</title>
	</header>
	<body>
		<p>
Here are some more documentation if you want to know more than just make the demos.</p>
		<section>
			<title>The linguistic files</title>

<p>Files for OAHPA are in the ped-directory, here is used sme (North Saami) and nob (Norwegian) as example. </p>

<p><strong>Generating the database of word forms, the files are in sme/src/ or sme/meta/:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><code>N_smenob.xml</code> and <code>N_paradigms.txt</code>  (in paradigms are the tags for generation, one pair for each PoS)</li>
<li><code>Adv_smenob.xml, Mwe_smenob.xml</code> (only for Leksa, no paradigms)</li>
<li><code>semantic_sets.xml</code> (semantic categories of semantic sets)</li>
<li><code>Pron_sme.xml</code> (containing paradigms, only for Morfa)</li>
<li><code>Names.xml</code> (person names, only for Morfa) </li>
<li><code>fillings.xml</code> (words of other POS) </li>
<li><code>tags.txt</code> </li>
<li><code>gt/bin/isme-GG.restr.fst</code> (for generation of the western dialect) </li>
<li><code>gt/bin/isme-KJ.restr.fst</code> (for generation of the eastern dialect)</li>
<li><code>gt/bin/isme-norm.fst</code> (for generation of the key answers)</li>
</ul>
<p></p>
<p><a href="generation.html">Read more about generation of word forms.</a></p>


<p></p>

<p><strong>Files especially for Leksa, from Norwegian to North Sami, in nobsrc/:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><code>A_nobsme.xml</code>, (for each PoS)</li>
</ul>

<p></p>

<p><strong>Automata for Numra:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><code>sme-Num.fst</code></li>
</ul>


<p></p>
<p><strong>Files for generating tasks in Morfa-C and Vasta, in sme/meta/:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><code>N_questions.xml</code> (one file for each PoS in Morfa C)</li>
<li><code>vastas_questions.xml</code></li>
<li><code>grammar_defaults.xml</code> (takes care of agreement in Morfa C tasks) </li>
</ul>
<p></p>


<p><strong>Dialogue files for Sahka, in sme/meta/:</strong></p> 
<ul>
<li><code>dialogue_firstmeeting.xml</code> (one of many dialogues)</li>
<li><code>dialogues.dtd</code></li>
</ul>

<p></p>

<p><strong>Files for giving feedback about morphology in Morfa-S:</strong></p><p> The feedback-files add feedbacktags based on a combination of the morphological features specified in the lexicon, and the task itself. With help of the tags the system generates feedback messages for the user. In sme/meta/:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>feedback_N.xml</code> (one file for each Morfa C PoS</li>
<li><code>messages.xml</code> (one file for each metalanguage)</li>
</ul>
<p></p>
<p><strong>Other files offering help to the user, in sme/meta/:</strong></p>
<p><code>comments.xml (nob, eng, sme, swe, fin)</code> (comments to the user aobut how she is succeeding with the tasks.)</p>
<p><code>grammatikklinker.txt (nob, eng, sme, swe, fin)</code> (links to the grammar documentation. The grammar files are in userdoc/) </p>
<p></p>
<p><a href="feedback.html">Read more about feedback.</a></p>
<p></p>

<p><strong>Files for analysing the free input in Sahka and Vasta:</strong></p>

<p><code>ped-sme.fst</code> gives morphological analysis to the user's input. It is normative, but it allows proper nouns written with small initial letter, but marks it with an error tag.</p>
<p><code>sme-ped.cg3</code> disambuguates and adds grammar error and navigation tags to the user's input.</p>
<p></p>

<p><strong>Files for giving feedback in Vasta and Sahka:</strong></p><p>The feedback messages are generated with help of the grammartags in the analysis done with the vislcg3-file, in sme/meta/:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>messages_vasta.xml, (nob, eng, sme, swe, fin)</code></li>
</ul>

</section>
		<section>
			<title>System files</title>

<p>In<code> univ_oahpa/</code> are files system files:</p>

<ul>
<li>installation scripts</li>
<li><code>media/</code> : images</li>
<li><code>templates/</code> : html-files for basic look for all the programs</li>
<li><code>drill/</code> : scripts for each program</li>
<li><code>drill/templates/</code>  : html-files for each program</li>
<li><code>locale/</code>  : localisation </li>
</ul>
<p></p>

<p>In <code>userdoc/ </code>are files for userdocumentation and the North Sami grammar.</p>


</section>


	</body>
</document>