<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Introduction to OAHPA-davvi</title>
  </header>

  <body>
  <p><a href="OAHPAveiledning.html">Sámegillii</a> | <a href="OAHPAveiledning.nob.html">På norsk</a> | <em>In English</em> | <a href="OAHPAveiledning.fin.html">Suomeksi</a> | <a href="OAHPAveiledning.swe.html">På svenska</a></p>
  
  <p></p>

    <p><a href="http://oahpa.no/davvi/"><em class="focus">OAHPA-davvi</em></a> is not an entire course. It is a learner's aid for acquisition of the Northern Sami language. The programs have many choices and therefore can be suited to the students. We have have drafted a brief introduction to each of the programs: </p>
 <ul>
      <li><a href="numra.eng.html"><em class="focus">Numra</em></a> - practice with numbers</li>
      <li><a href="leksa.eng.html"><em class="focus">Leksa</em></a> - practice with words and place names</li>
      <li><a href="morfa.eng.html"><em class="focus">Morfa</em></a> - inflection of words, individual words or in sentences</li>
      <li><a href="vasta.eng.html"><em class="focus">Vasta</em></a> - answer questions</li>
      <li><a href="sahka.eng.html"><em class="focus">Sahka</em></a> - participate in dialogues</li>
    </ul> 
<p></p>

<p>Our goal is for the students to practice vocabulary that is typical for beginners. In many of the programs it is possible for the student to limit the vocabulary to what is given in the books used. If the student would prefer to work on vocabulary according to subject, he/she can select <a href="satnevuorka.eng.html"><em class="focus">thematic word lists.</em></a></p>


    <p>We have drawn up a <a href="grammatihkka.eng.html"><em class="focus">minigrammar</em></a> where each word class is explained with examples and inflections. The students have access to this grammar via a window in the upper right corner in the OAHPA-programs. </p>

    <p>The students can choose between <em class="focus">western and eastern dialect</em>. This means that the vocabulary, inflectional patterns and explanations are given according to the dialect selected, for example, trisyllabic verbs in the present: "mii muitalat" (eastern), "mii muitalit" (western). But the program will approve all correct spellings of the Sami words regardless of the dialect selected. </p>


    <p>We have programs for those who already know Sami pretty well, but who wish to learn about grammar and syntax - <a href="http://oahpa.no/sme/usevisl/VISL_spealut.html"><em class="focus">VISL-games</em></a> - see in the left margin. <a href="Killerfiller_eng.html"><em class="focus">Killerfiller</em></a> also has levels for those who are only beginning to learn Sami.</p>
    
    
    <p>In the left margin under <em class="focus">Aids</em> you will find generation of inflectional paradigms, dictionaries, word and text analysis, as well as articles on word classes and sentence analysis.</p>

    <p>Some of the programs are <em class="focus">beta-versions</em>, and this means that there might be errors and possibilities for improvement. We will be happy to hear your comments! (oahpa@hum.uit.no) </p>
     

      <p><a href="techspec.eng.html">Technical specifications</a></p>

      <p><a href="birra.eng.html">About the project</a></p>

  </body>
</document>
