<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Introduction to OAHPA-davvi</title>
  </header>

  <body>
<!--<p><a href="http://oahpa.uit.no/"><em>OAHPA!-hovedside</em></a> </p> -->     
<p><a href="OAHPAveiledning.html">Sámegillii</a></p>
  
  <p></p>

    <p><a href="http://oahpa.uit.no/univ_oahpa/">OAHPA-davvi</a> is both part of a full course in Sami, and it may work as a supplement to other courses. The programs have many options, and may be adjusted to different levels. We have made an introduction to each program: </p>
 <ul>
      <li><a href="numra.eng.html">Numra</a>, practice numerals</li>
      <li><a href="leksa.eng.html">Leksa</a>, practice words and place names</li>
      <li><a href="morfa.eng.html">Morfa</a>, inflect words, in isolation or in sentential contexts</li>
      <li><a href="vasta.eng.html">Vasta</a>, answer to questions</li>
      <li><a href="sahka.eng.html">Sahka</a>, participate in dialogues</li>
    </ul> 
<p></p>

<p>Our goal is to let the students practice basic vocabulary, and in several of the programs they can limit the vocabulary to what is found in the textbook they use. If you would rather like to work with specific themes, you may print out <a href="satnevuorka.eng.html">thematic word lists.</a></p>


    <p>We made a <a href="../gramm/grammatihkka.eng.html">grammar</a> where each part of speech is explained, with examples from inflection and use. The pupils have access to this grammar via a window in the upper right corner in the OAHPA programs. </p>

    <p>The pupils may choose between <strong>western and eastern dialect</strong>. This means that vocabulary, inflectional patterns and explanations are adjusted to the dialct choosen, e.g. for odd-syllabic verbs in present tense: "mii muitalat" (eastern), "mii muitalit" (western). The program will accept all forms from the pupil, though, also mixed dialect forms, as long as they are within the official Sami orthography. </p>


    <p>We also have programs for pupils with advanced Sami skills that want to learn more about grammar and syntax  - <a href="http://victorio.uit.no/oahpa/visl/">the VISL games</a> - have a look at the VISL link in the margin. <a href="../usevisl/Killerfiller_nob.html">Killerfiller</a> also has tasks for beginner students.</p>
    
    
    <p>The link <strong>Resources</strong> gives paradigm generation, dictionary, word and text analysis, and articles on part of speech and sentence analysis.</p>

    <p>Some of these additional programs are still <strong>beta versions</strong>, which means that they may contain errors. Comments are welcome! (oahpa@hum.uit.no) </p>
     

      <p><a href="techspec.eng.html">Technical specifications</a></p>

      <p><a href="birra.eng.html">About the project</a></p>

  </body>
</document>
