<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Welcome to the OAHPA! portal!</title>
  </header>

  <body>
       <p><a href="index.html">Sámegillii</a>  | <a href="index.nob.html">På norsk</a> | <em>In English</em></p>
  
    <p>The Universitety of Tromsø makes pedagogical programs for learning North Sámi. We offer programs for South Sámi as well.</p>


    <p><strong>The OAHPA! programs</strong> are made for language learning, and they are made at the University of Tromsø. You can test them via <a href="http://oahpa.no/davvi/">OAHPA main page</a> or you can use the links on the left side.</p>

<p></p>

    <p><a href="http://oahpa.no/sme/usevisl/VISL_spealut.eng.html"><strong>The VISL programs</strong></a> are made in order to learn grammar, and they are better suited for people who already know Sámi. The VISL group at Syd-Dansk Universitet is responsible for the technique, and the University of Tromsø has added North Sámi content.</p>
    
<p></p>    
    <p><strong>Teaching resources</strong> include generation of inflectional paradigms, dictionary, word- and text analysis, and articles treating parts of speech and sentence analysis. You find them on the left margin.</p>


<p><strong>Our goal</strong> is to make it possible for the users to train everyday language. The basis for this is a set of words used in beginners' education, cf. the Oahpa-vocabulary page. But we may also make teaching material for special themes, e.g. Sámi handicraft. Contact us if you have suggestions or special needs! </p>

    <p>Some of the resources are <strong>beta-versions</strong>, which means that they may contain errors, and that there is a potential for improvement. We are indeed open to comments! (oahpa@hum.uit.no) </p>
     

      <p><a href="useoahpa/techspec.eng.html">Technical spesifications and links</a></p>

      <p><a href="usevisl/resurssat.eng.html">Resources on other sites</a></p>

      <p><a href="useoahpa/birra.eng.html">About the project</a></p>

  </body>
</document>
